Please welcome AI researcher and founding member of OpenAI, Andrej Karpathy.
Andrej Karpathy Hi, everyone.
I'm happy to be here to tell you about the state of GPT and more generally about the
rapidly growing ecosystem of large language models.
So I would like to partition the talk into two parts.
In the first part, I would like to tell you about how we train GPT assistants.
And then in the second part, we are going to take a look at how we can use these assistants
effectively for your applications.
So first, let's take a look at the emerging recipe for how to train these assistants.
And keep in mind that this is all very new and still rapidly evolving.
But so far, the recipe looks something like this.
Now this is kind of a complicated slide, so I'm going to go through it piece by piece.
But roughly speaking, we have four major stages, pre-training, supervised fine-tuning,
reward modeling, reinforcement learning, and they follow each other serially.
Now in each stage, we have a data set that powers that stage.
We have an algorithm that for our purposes will be an objective for training the neural
network.
And then we have a resulting model.
And then there's some notes on the bottom.
So the first stage we're going to start with is the pre-training stage.
Now this stage is kind of special in this diagram, and this diagram is not to scale.
Because this stage is where all of the computational work basically happens.
This is 99% of the training compute time, and also flops.
And so this is where we are dealing with internet-scale data sets with thousands of GPUs in the supercomputer,
and also months of training, potentially.
The other three stages are fine-tuning stages that are much more along the lines of a small
few number of GPUs and hours or days.
So let's take a look at the pre-training stage to achieve a base model.
First we're going to gather a large amount of data.
Here's an example of what we call a data mixture that comes from this paper that was released
by Meta, where they released this LAMA base model.
Now you can see roughly the kinds of data sets that enter into these collections.
So we have Common Crawl, which is just a web scrape, C4, which is also Common Crawl, and
then some high-quality data sets as well.
So for example, GitHub, Wikipedia, and so on.
So we have common crawl, which is just a web scrape, C4, which is also common crawl, and then some high-quality data sets as well. So for example, GitHub, Wikipedia, and so on.
So we have Common Crawl, which is just a web scrape, C4, which is also common crawl, and then some high-quality data sets as well.
These are all mixed up together, and then they are sampled according to some given proportions,
and that forms the training set for the neural net, for the GPT.
Now before we can actually train on this data, we need to go through one more pre-processing
step, and that is tokenization.
And this is basically a translation of the raw text that we scraped from the internet
into sequences of integers.
Because that's the native representation over which GPTs function.
Now, this is a lossless method of group mapping.
lossless kind of translation between pieces of text and tokens and integers. And there are a
number of algorithms for this stage. Typically, for example, you could use something like byte
pairing coding, which iteratively merges little text chunks and groups them into tokens. And so
here I'm showing some example chunks of these tokens. And then this is the raw integer sequence
that will actually feed into a transformer. Now, here I'm showing two sort of like examples for
hyperparameters that govern this stage. So GPT-4, we did not release too much information about how
it was trained and so on. So I'm using GPT-3's numbers. But GPT-3 is, of course, a little bit
old by now, about three years ago. But LAMA is a fairly recent model from Meta. So these are
roughly the orders of magnitude that we're dealing with when we're doing pre-training.
The vocabulary size is usually a couple 10,000 tokens. The context length is usually something
like 2,000, 4,000, or nowadays even 100,000. And this governs the maximum number of integers
that we're dealing with. And so this is the order of magnitude that we're dealing with.
That the GPT will look at when it's trying to predict the next integer in a sequence.
You can see that roughly the number of parameters is, say, 65 billion for LAMA.
Now, even though LAMA has only 65B parameters compared to GPT-3's 175 billion parameters,
LAMA is a significantly more powerful model. And intuitively, that's because the model is
trained for significantly longer. In this case, 1.4 trillion tokens instead of just 300 billion
tokens. So you shouldn't judge the power of a model just by the number of parameters that it
contains.
Below, I'm showing some tables of rough hyperparameters that typically go into specifying
the transformer neural network. So the number of heads, the dimension size, number of layers,
and so on. And on the bottom, I'm showing some training hyperparameters. So for example,
to train the 65B model, Meta used 2,000 GPUs, roughly 21 days of training, and roughly several
million dollars. And so that's the rough orders of magnitude that you should have in mind for the
pre-training stage.
Now, when we're actually pre-training, what happens? Roughly speaking, we are going to take our tokens,
and we're going to lay them out into data batches. So we have these arrays that will feed into the
transformer, and these arrays are B, the batch size, and these are all independent examples stacked
up in rows, and B by T, T being the maximum context length. So in my picture, I only have 10,
the context length. So this could be 2,000, 4,000, et cetera. So these are extremely long rows. And what we do is we take these
documents, and we pack them into rows, and we delimit them with these special end-of-text tokens, basically telling the
transformer where a new document begins. And so here I have a few examples of documents, and then I've stretched them out
into this input. Now, we're going to feed all of these numbers into transformer. And let me just focus on a single
particular cell, but the same thing will happen at every cell in this diagram. So let's look at the green cell. The green cell is
going to take a look at all of the tokens before it, so all of the tokens in yellow, and we're going to feed that entire context into the
transformer neural network, and the transformer is going to try to predict the next token in a sequence, in this case, in red. Now, the
transformer, I don't have too much time to, unfortunately, go into the full details of this neural network architecture. It's just a large blob of
neural net stuff for our purposes, and it's got several 10 billion parameters, typically, or something like that. And, of course, as you
tune these parameters, you're getting slightly different predicted distributions. And so what we're going to do is we're going to take a look at the
distributions for every single one of these cells. And so, for example, if our vocabulary size is 50,257 tokens, then we're going to have that
many numbers, because we need to specify a probability distribution for what comes next. So basically, we have a probability for whatever may
follow. Now, in this specific example, for this specific cell, 513 will come next, and so we can use this as a source of supervision to update our
transformer's weights. And so we're applying this, basically, on every single cell in the parallel, and we keep swapping back and forth between the
batches, and we're trying to get the transformer to make the correct predictions over what token comes next in a sequence. So let me show you more
concretely what this looks like when you train one of these models. This is actually coming from the New York Times, and they trained a small GPT on
Shakespeare. And so here's a small snippet of Shakespeare, and they trained a GPT on it. Now, in the beginning, at initialization, the GPT starts with
completely random weights, so you're just getting completely random outputs as well. But over time, as you train the GPT longer and longer,
you are getting more and more coherent and consistent sort of samples from the model. And the way you sample from it, of course, is you predict what comes
next, you sample from that distribution, and you keep feeding that back into the process, and you can basically sample large sequences. And so by the end, you see
that the transformer has learned about words and where to put spaces and where to put commas and so on. And so we're making more and more consistent
predictions over time. These are the kinds of plots that you're looking at when you're doing model pre-training. Effectively, we're looking at
a loss function over time as you train, and low loss means that our transformer is predicting the correct, is giving a higher probability to get the correct next
integer in a sequence. Now, what are we going to do with this model once we've trained it after a month? Well, the first thing that we noticed, we, the field, is that
these models basically, in the process of language modeling, learn very powerful general representations, and it's possible to very efficiently fine-tune them
for any arbitrary downstream task you might be interested in.
So as an example, if you're interested in sentiment classification, the approach used to be that you collect a bunch of positives and negatives, and then you train some kind of an NLP model for that.
But the new approach is, ignore sentiment classification, go off and do large language model pre-training, train the large transformer, and then you can only, you may only have a few examples, and you can very efficiently fine-tune your model for that task.
And so this works very well in practice, and the reason for this is that basically, the transformer is
forced to multitask a huge amount of tasks in the language modeling task, because just in terms of
predicting the next token, it's forced to understand a lot about the structure of the text
and all the different concepts therein. So that was GPT-1. Now, around the time of GPT-2, people
noticed that actually even better than fine-tuning, you can actually prompt these models very
effectively. So these are language models, and they want to complete documents. So you can actually
trick them into performing tasks just by arranging these fake documents. So in this example,
for example, we have some passage, and then we sort of like do QA, QA, QA. This is called a few-shot
prompt. And then we do Q. And then as the transformer is trying to complete the document,
it's actually answering our question. And so this is an example of prompt engineering a base model,
making it believe that it's sort of imitating a document and getting it to perform a task.
And so this picked off, I think, the era of, I would say, prompting over fine-tuning and seeing
that this actually works. And so this is an example of prompt engineering a base model,
actually can work extremely well on a lot of problems, even without training any neural
networks, fine-tuning, or so on. Now, since then, we've seen an entire evolutionary tree of base
models that everyone has trained. Not all of these models are available. For example, the GPT-4 base
model was never released. The GPT-4 model that you might be interacting with over API is not a base
model. It's an assistant model. And we're going to cover how to get those in a bit. GPT-3 base
model is available via the API under the name DaVinci.
And GPT-2 base model is available even as weights on our GitHub repo. But currently,
the best available base model probably is the Lama series from Meta, although it is not
commercially licensed. Now, one thing to point out is base models are not assistants. They don't
want to make answers to your questions. They just want to complete documents. So if you tell them,
write a poem about the bread and cheese, it will answer questions with more questions. It's just
completing what it thinks is a document. However, you can prompt them in a specific way for base
models that is more likely to work. So as an example, here's a poem about bread and cheese. And in
that case, it will autocomplete correctly. You can even trick base models into being assistants. And
the way you would do this is you would create like a specific few-shot prompt that makes it look like
there's some kind of a document between a human and assistant, and they're exchanging sort of
information. And then at the bottom, you sort of put your query at the end.
And the base model will sort of like condition itself into being like a helpful assistant and kind of
answer. But this is not very reliable and doesn't work super well in practice, although it can be
done. So instead, we have a different path to make actual GPT assistants, not just base model document
completers. And so that takes us into supervised fine-tuning. So in the supervised fine-tuning
stage, we are going to collect small but high-quality data sets. And in this case, we're going to ask
you to collect a set of the form prompt and ideal response. And we're going to collect lots of these,
typically tens of thousands or something like that. And then we're going to still do language
modeling on this data. So nothing changed algorithmically. We're just swapping out a
training set. So it used to be internet documents, which is a high-quantity, low-quality, for
basically a QA prompt response kind of data. And that is low-quantity, high-quality. So we
still do language modeling, and then after training, we get an SFD model. And you can
see these models, and they are actual assistants, and they work to some extent. Let me show you what
an example demonstration might look like. So here's something that a human contractor might
come up with. Here's some random prompt. Can you write a short introduction about the relevance of
the term monopsony or something like that? And then the contractor also writes out an ideal
response. And when they write out these responses, they are following extensive labeling documentations,
and they are being asked to be helpful, truthful, and harmless. And this is labeling instructions
here. You probably can't read it.
Neither can I. But they're long, and this is just people following instructions and trying to
complete these prompts. So that's what the data set looks like, and you can train these models,
and this works to some extent. Now, you can actually continue the pipeline from here on and
go into RLHF, reinforcement learning from human feedback, that consists of both reward modeling
and reinforcement learning. So let me cover that, and then I'll come back to why you may want to go
through the extra steps and how that compares to just SFD models. So in the reward modeling step,
we're now going to shift our data collection to be of the form of comparisons. So here's an example
of what our data set will look like. I have the same prompt, identical prompt on the top,
which is asking the assistant to write a program or a function that checks if a given string is
a palindrome. And then what we do is we take the SFD model, which we've already trained,
and we create multiple completions. So in this case, we have three completions that the model
has created. And then we ask people to rank these completions. So if you stare at this for a while,
these are very difficult things to do to compare some of these predictions. And this can take
people even hours for a single prompt completion pairs. But let's say we decided that one of these
is much better than the others and so on. So we rank them. Then we can follow that with something
that looks very much kind of like a binary classification on all the possible pairs
between these completions. So what we do now is we lay out our prompt in rows, and the prompts
is identical across all three rows here. So it's all the same prompt, but the completion does vary.
So the yellow tokens are coming from the SFD model. Then what we do is we append another
special reward readout token at the end. And we basically only supervise the transformer at this
single green token. And the transformer will predict some reward for how good that completion
is for that prompt. And so basically, it makes a guess about the quality of each completion. And
then once it makes a guess for every one of them, we also have the ground truth, which is telling
us the ranking of them. And so we can actually enforce that. And so we can actually enforce that,
some of these numbers should be much higher than others and so on. We formulate this into a loss
function, and we train our model to make reward predictions that are consistent with the ground
truth coming from the comparisons from all these contractors. So that's how we train our reward
model. And that allows us to score how good a completion is for a prompt. Once we have a reward
model, we can't deploy this because this is not very useful as an assistant by itself, but it's
very useful for the reinforcement learning stage that follows now. Because we have a reward model,
we can score
the quality of any arbitrary completion for any given prompt. So what we do during reinforcement
learning is we basically get, again, a large collection of prompts. And now we do reinforcement
learning with respect to the reward model. So here's what that looks like. We take a single
prompt, we lay it out in rows, and now we use basically the model we'd like to train,
which is initialized at SFT model, to create some completions in yellow. And then we append
the reward token again, and we read off the reward according to the reward model, which
is now kept fixed. It doesn't change anymore. And now the reward model tells us the quality of every
single completion for these prompts. And so what we can do is we can now just basically apply the
same language modeling loss function, but we're currently training on the yellow tokens, and we
are weighing the language modeling objective by the rewards indicated by the reward model. So as
an example, in the first row, the reward model said that this is a fairly high scoring completion,
and so all of the tokens that we happened to
on the first row are going to get reinforced and they're going to get higher probabilities
for the future. Conversely, on the second row, the reward model really did not like this completion,
negative 1.2. And so therefore, every single token that we sampled in that second row is going to
get a slightly higher probability for the future. And we do this over and over on many prompts,
on many batches. And basically, we get a policy which creates yellow tokens here. And it basically,
all of them, all of the completions here will score high according to the reward model that
we trained in the previous stage. So that's how we train. That's what the RLHF pipeline is.
Now, and then at the end, you get a model that you could deploy. And so as an example,
ChatGPT is an RLHF model. But some other models that you might come across, like for example,
the Kuna 13b and so on, these are SFT models. So we have base models, SFT models, and RLHF models.
And that's kind of like the state of things there. Now, why would you want to do RLHF?
So one answer that is kind of...
not that exciting, is that it just works better. So this comes from the InstructGPT paper.
According to these experiments a while ago now, these PPO models are RLHF.
And we see that they are basically just preferred in a lot of comparisons
when we give them to humans. So humans just prefer out
basically tokens that come from RLHF models compared to SFT models, compared to base model that is prompted to be an assistant.
And so it just works better. But you might ask why?
Why does it work better? And I don't think that there's a single
like amazing answer that the community has really like agreed on, but I will just offer one reason, potentially.
And it has to do with the asymmetry between how easy computationally it is to compare versus generate.
So let's take an example of generating a haiku. Suppose I ask a model to write a haiku about paperclips.
If you're a contractor trying to give training data, then imagine being a contractor collecting basically data for the SFT stage.
How are you supposed to create a nice haiku for a paperclip? You might just not be very good at that.
But if I give you a few examples of haikus, you might be able to appreciate some of these haikus a lot more than others.
And so judging which one of these is good is a much easier task.
And so basically this asymmetry makes it so that comparisons are a better way to potentially
leverage yourself as a human and your judgment to create a slightly better model.
Now, RLHF models are not strictly an improvement on the base models in some cases.
So in particular, we've noticed, for example, that they lose some entropy.
So that means that they give more
peaky results. They can output lower variations, like they can output samples with lower variation than base model.
So base model has lots of entropy and will give lots of diverse outputs.
So, for example, one kind of place where I still prefer to use a base model is in a setup where you basically have n things and you want to generate more things like it.
And so here is an example that I just cooked up.
I want to generate cool Pokemon names.
I gave it seven Pokemon names, and I asked the base model to complete the document, and it gave me a lot more Pokemon names.
These are fictitious. I tried to look them up. I don't believe they're actual Pokemons.
And this is the kind of task that I think base model would be good at, because it still has lots of entropy.
It will give you lots of diverse, cool, kind of more things that look like whatever you give it before.
So this is what, this is number, having said all that, these are kind of like the assistant models
that are probably available to you at this point.
There's a team at Berkeley,
that ranked a lot of the available assistant models and gave them basically ELO ratings.
So currently some of the best models, of course, are GPT-4, by far, I would say, followed by Clawed, GPT-3.5,
and then a number of models, some of these might be available as weights, like the Kuna, Koala, etc.
And the first three rows here, they're all RLHF models, and all of the other models, to my knowledge, are SFT models, I believe.
Okay, so that's how we train these models.
On the high level.
Now I'm going to switch gears, and let's look at how we can best apply a GPT assistant model to your problems.
Now, I would like to work in a setting of a concrete example.
So let's work with a concrete example here.
Let's say that you are working on an article or a blog post, and you're going to write this sentence at the end.
California's population is 53 times that of Alaska.
So for some reason, you want to compare the populations of these two states.
Think about the rich internal monologue and tool use,
and how much work actually goes computationally in your brain to generate this one final sentence.
So here's maybe what that could look like in your brain.
Okay, for this next step, let me blog, or my blog, let me compare these two populations.
Okay, first I'm going to obviously need to get both of these populations.
Now, I know that I probably don't know these populations off the top of my head.
So I'm kind of like aware of what I know or don't know of my self-knowledge, right?
So I go, I do some tool use, and I go to Wikipedia, and I look up California's population.
And Alaska's population.
Now I know that I should divide the two.
But again, I know that dividing 39.2 by 0.74 is very unlikely to succeed.
That's not the kind of thing that I can do in my head.
And so therefore, I'm going to rely on the calculator.
So I'm going to use a calculator, punch it in, and see that the output is roughly 53.
And then maybe I do some reflection and sanity checks in my brain.
So does 53 make sense?
Well, that's quite a large fraction, but then California is the most populous state.
So maybe that looks okay.
Okay.
So then I have all the information I might need.
And now I get to the sort of creative portion of writing.
So I might start to write something like, California has 53x times greater.
And then I think to myself, that's actually like really awkward phrasing.
So let me actually delete that, and let me try again.
And so as I'm writing, I have this separate process almost inspecting what I'm writing
and judging whether it looks good or not.
And then maybe I delete, and maybe I reframe it, and then maybe I'm happy with what comes out.
So basically, long story short, a ton happens.
So I'm writing this sentence under the hood in terms of your internal monologue when you
create sentences like this.
But what does a sentence like this look like when we are training a GPT on it?
From GPT's perspective, this is just a sequence of tokens.
So a GPT, when it's reading or generating these tokens, it just goes chunk, chunk,
chunk, chunk, chunk.
And each chunk is roughly the same amount of computational work for each token.
And these transformers are not very shallow networks.
They have about 80 layers of reasoning.
But 80 is still not like too much.
And so this transformer is going to do its best to imitate.
But of course, the process here looks very, very different from the process that you took.
So in particular, in our final artifacts, in the data sets that we create and then eventually feed
to LLMs, all of that internal dialogue is completely stripped.
And unlike you, the GPT will look at every single token and spend the same amount of
compute on every one of them.
And so you can't expect it to actually like, well, you can't expect it to do,
sort of do too much work per token.
And also in particular, basically these transformers are just like token simulators.
So they don't know what they don't know.
Like they just imitate the next token.
They don't know what they're good at or not good at.
They just tried their best to imitate the next token.
They don't reflect in the loop.
They don't sanity check anything.
They don't correct their mistakes along the way by default.
They just sample token sequences.
They don't have separate inner monologue streams in their head, right?
They're evaluating what's happening.
Now, they do have some.
A sort of cognitive advantages, I would say, and that is that they do actually have very
large fact based knowledge across a vast number of areas because they have, say, several 10
billion parameters.
So that's a lot of storage for a lot of facts.
But and they also, I think, have a relatively large and perfect working memory.
So whatever fixed into the whatever fits into the context window is immediately available
to the transformer through its internal self attention mechanism.
And so it's kind of like perfect memory, but it's got a finite size.
The transformer has a very direct access to it, and so it can like a losslessly remember
anything that is inside its context window.
So that's kind of how I would compare those two.
And the reason I bring all of this up is because I think to a large extent, prompting is just
making up for this sort of cognitive difference between these two kind of architectures like
our brains here and LLM brains.
You can look at it that way almost.
So here's one thing that people found, for example, works pretty well in practice, especially
if your tasks require reasoning.
You can't expect the transformer to make to do too much reasoning per token.
And so you have to really spread out the reasoning across more and more tokens.
So, for example, you can't give a transformer a very complicated question and expect it
to get the answer in a single token.
There's just not enough time for it.
These transformers need tokens to think, quote unquote, I like to say sometimes.
And so this is some of the things that work well.
You may, for example, have a few shot prompt that shows the transformer that it should
like show its work when it's answering the question when it's answering a question.
And if you give a few examples, the transformer will imitate that template and it will just
end up working out better in terms of its evaluation.
Additionally, you can elicit this kind of behavior from the transformer by saying, let's
think step by step, because this conditioned the transformer into sort of like showing
its work.
And because it kind of snaps into a mode of showing its work, it's going to do less
computational work per token.
And so it's more likely to succeed as a result because it's making slower reasoning over
time.
Here's another example.
This one is called self-consistency.
We saw that we had the ability to start writing and then if it didn't work out, I can try
again and I can try multiple times and and maybe select the one that worked best.
So in these kinds of approaches, you may sample not just once, but you may sample multiple
times and then have some process for finding the ones that are good and then keeping just
those samples or doing a majority vote or something like that.
So basically, these transformers in the process as they predict the next token.
Just like you, they can get unlucky and they could they could sample and not a very good
token and they can go down sort of like a blind alley in terms of reasoning.
And so unlike you, they cannot recover from that.
They are stuck with every single token they sample, and so they will continue the sequence
even if they even know that this sequence is not going to work out.
So give them the ability to look back, inspect or try to find, try to basically sample around
it.
Here's one technique.
Also, you could.
It turns out that actually, LLMs.
Like, they know they're going to be able to do it.
They know they're going to be able to do it.
They know when they've screwed up.
So as an example, say you asked the model to generate a poem that does not rhyme, and
it might give you a poem, but it actually rhymes.
But it turns out that especially for the bigger models like GPT-4, you can just ask it, did
you meet the assignment?
And actually, GPT-4 knows very well that it did not meet the assignment.
It just kind of got unlucky in its sampling.
And so it will tell you, no, I didn't actually meet the assignment here.
Let me try again.
But without you prompting it, it doesn't even like it doesn't know it doesn't know
to revisit and and so on.
So you have to make up for that in your prompts.
You have to get it to check.
If you don't ask it to check, it's not going to check by itself.
It's just a token simulator.
I think more generally, a lot of these techniques fall into the bucket of what I would say recreating
our system, too.
So you might be familiar with the system one system to thinking for humans.
System one is a fast automatic process, and I think kind of corresponds to like an LLM
just sampling tokens and system two is the slower, the
deliberate planning sort of part of your brain.
And so this is a paper actually from just last week because this space is pretty quickly
evolving.
It's called Tree of Thought and in Tree of Thought, the authors of this paper proposed
maintaining multiple completions for any given prompt, and then they are also scoring them
along the way and keeping the ones that are going well, if that makes sense.
And so a lot of people are like really playing around with kind of prompt engineering to
basically.
Bring back some of these abilities that we sort of have in our brain for LLMs.
Now, one thing I would like to note here is that this is not just a prompt.
This is actually prompts that are together used with some Python glue code because you
don't you actually have to maintain multiple prompts and you also have to do some tree
search algorithm here to figure out which prompts to expand, etc.
So it's a symbiosis of Python glue code and individual prompts that are called in a while
loop or in a bigger algorithm.
I also think there's a really cool parallel here to AlphaGo.
AlphaGo has a policy for placing the next stone when it plays go, and this policy was
trained originally by imitating humans.
But in addition to this policy, it also does multi-color tree search, and basically it
will play out a number of possibilities in its head and evaluate all of them and only
keep the ones that work well.
And so I think this is kind of an equivalent of AlphaGo, but for text, if that makes sense.
So just like Tree of Thought, I think more generally people are starting to really explore
more general techniques of not just the simple question answer prompts, but something
that looks a lot more like Python glue code stringing together many prompts.
So on the right, I have an example from this paper called React, where they structure the
answer to a prompt as a sequence of thought, action, observation, thought, action, observation,
and it's a full rollout, a kind of a thinking process to answer the query.
And in these actions, the model is also allowed to tool use.
On the left.
I have an example of AutoGPT.
And now AutoGPT, by the way, is a project that I think got a lot of hype recently, but
I think I still find it kind of inspirationally interesting.
It's a project that allows an LLM to sort of keep a task list and continue to recursively
break down tasks.
And I don't think this currently works very well, and I would not advise people to use
it in practical applications.
I just think it's something to generally take inspiration from in terms of where this is
going, I think, over time.
So that's kind of like giving our model system to thinking.
The next thing that I find kind of interesting is this following sort of, I would say, almost
psychological quirk of LLMs is that LLMs don't want to succeed.
They want to imitate.
You want to succeed, and you should ask for it.
So what I mean by that is when Transformers are trained, they have training sets, and
there can be an entire spectrum of performance qualities in their training data.
So, for example, there could be some kind of a prompt for some physics question or something
like that, and there could be a student solution that is completely wrong, but there can also
be an expert answer that is extremely right.
And Transformers can't tell the difference between like, I mean, they know about low
quality solutions and high quality solutions, but by default, they want to imitate all of
it because they're just trained on language modeling.
And so at test time, you actually have to ask for a good performance.
So in this example, in this paper, they tried various prompts.
Let's think step by step was very powerful because it sort of like spread out the reasoning
over many tokens.
But what worked even better is let's work this out in a step by step way to be sure we
have the right answer.
And so it's kind of like conditioning on getting the right answer.
And this actually makes the Transformer work better because the Transformer doesn't have
to now hedge its probability mass on low quality solutions.
As ridiculous as that sounds.
And so basically, don't feel free to ask for a strong solution.
Say something like you are a leading expert on this topic.
Pretend you have IQ 120.
Et cetera.
But don't try to ask for too much IQ because if you ask for IQ like 400, you might be out
of data distribution or even worse, you could be in data distribution for some like sci-fi
stuff and it will start to like take on some sci-fi like role playing or something like
that.
So you have to find like the right amount of IQ.
I think it's got some U-shaped curve there.
Next up, as we saw when we are trying to solve problems, we know what we are good at and
what we're not good at.
And we lean on tools.
Computationally.
You want to do the same potentially with your LLMs.
So in particular, we may want to give them calculators, code interpreters, and so on.
The ability to do search.
And there's a lot of techniques for doing that.
One thing to keep in mind again is that these Transformers by default may not know what
they don't know.
So you may even want to tell the Transformer in a prompt, you are not very good at mental
arithmetic.
Whenever you need to do very large number addition, multiplication, or whatever, you're
going to use this calculator.
Here's how you use the calculator.
Use this token combination, et cetera, et cetera.
So you have to actually like spell it out because the model by default doesn't know
what it's good at or not good at necessarily.
Just like you and I might be.
Next up, I think something that is very interesting is we went from a world that was retrieval
only all the way the pendulum has swung to the other extreme where it's memory only in
LLMs.
But actually, there's this entire space in between of these retrieval augmented models.
And this was a very interesting thing.
This works extremely well in practice.
As I mentioned, the context window of a Transformer is its working memory.
If you can load the working memory with any information that is relevant to the task,
the model will work extremely well because it can immediately access all that memory.
And so I think a lot of people are really interested in basically retrieval augmented
generation.
And on the bottom, I have like an example of LLMA index, which is one sort of data connector
to lots of different types of data.
And you can make it.
You can index all of that data, and you can make it accessible to LLMs.
And the emerging recipe there is you take relevant documents, you split them up into
chunks, you embed all of them, and you basically get embedding vectors that represent that
data.
You store that in the vector store, and then at test time, you make some kind of a query
to your vector store, and you fetch chunks that might be relevant to your task, and you
stuff them into the prompt, and then you generate.
So this can work quite well in practice.
So this is, I think, similar to when you and I solve problems, you can do everything from
your memory, and transformers have very large and extensive memory.
But also, it really helps to reference some primary documents.
So whenever you find yourself going back to a textbook to find something, or whenever
you find yourself going back to documentation of a library to look something up, the transformers
definitely want to do that too.
You have some memory over how some documentation of a library works, but it's much better to
look it up.
So the same applies here.
Next, I wanted to briefly talk about constraint prompting.
I also find this very useful.
Very interesting.
This is basically techniques for forcing a certain template in the outputs of LLMs.
So guidance is one example from Microsoft, actually.
And here we are enforcing that the output from the LLM will be JSON.
And this will actually guarantee that the output will take on this form, because they
go in and they mess with the probabilities of all the different tokens that come out
of the transformer, and they clamp those tokens.
And then the transformer is only filling in the blanks here.
And then you can enforce additional restrictions on what could go into those blanks.
So this might be really helpful.
And I think this kind of constraint sampling is also extremely interesting.
I also wanted to say a few words about fine tuning.
It is the case that you can get really far with prompt engineering, but it's also possible
to think about fine tuning your models.
Now, fine tuning models means that you are actually going to change the weights of the
model.
It is becoming a lot more accessible to do this in practice, and that's because of a
number of techniques that have been developed.
And I have libraries for very recently.
So, for example, parameter efficient fine tuning techniques like LoRa make sure that
you're only training small, sparse pieces of your model.
So most of the model is kept clamped at the base model, and some pieces of it are allowed
to change.
And this still works pretty well empirically, and makes it much cheaper to sort of tune
only small pieces of your model.
It also means that because most of your model is clamped, you can use very low precision
inference for computing those parts, because they are
not going to be updated by gradient descent.
And so that makes everything a lot more efficient as well.
And in addition, we have a number of open sourced, high quality based models.
Currently, as I mentioned, I think LAMA is quite nice, although it is not commercially
licensed, I believe, right now.
Something to keep in mind is that basically fine tuning is a lot more technically involved.
It requires a lot more, I think, technical expertise to do right.
It requires human data contractors for data sets and or synthetic data pipelines that
can be pretty complicated.
This will definitely slow down your iteration cycle by a lot.
And I would say on a high level, SFT is achievable, because it is just your continuing the language
modeling task.
It's relatively straightforward.
But RLHF, I would say, is very much research territory, and is even much harder to get
to work.
And so I would probably not advise that someone just tries to roll their own RLHF implementation.
These things are pretty unstable, very difficult to train, not something that is, I think,
very beginner friendly right now.
And it's also potentially likely, also.
To change pretty rapidly still.
So I think these are my sort of default recommendations right now.
I would break up your task into two major parts.
Number one, achieve your top performance.
And number two, optimize your performance, in that order.
Number one, the best performance will currently come from GFT4 model.
It is the most capable model by far.
Use prompts that are very detailed.
They have lots of task contents, relevant information and instructions.
Think along the lines of, what would you do?
Would you tell a task contractor if they can't email you back?
But then also keep in mind that a task contractor is a human, and they have inner monologue,
and they're very clever, et cetera.
LLMs do not possess those qualities.
So make sure to think through the psychology of the LLM, almost, and cater prompts to that.
Retrieve and add any relevant context and information to these prompts.
Basically refer to a lot of the prompt engineering techniques.
Some of them I've highlighted in the slides above.
But also, this is a very large space.
And I would just advise you to look for prompt engineering techniques online.
There's a lot to cover there.
Experiment with few-shot examples.
What this refers to is, you don't just want to tell.
You want to show, whenever it's possible.
So give it examples of everything.
That helps it really understand what you mean, if you can.
Experiment with tools and plug-ins to offload a task that are difficult for LLMs natively.
And then think about not just a single prompt and answer, think about potential chains and reflection,
and how you glue them together.
How you could potentially make multiple samples, and so on.
Finally, if you think you've squeezed out prompt engineering,
which I think you should stick with for a while,
look at some potentially fine-tuning a model to your application.
But expect this to be a lot more slower and involved.
And then there's an expert fragile research zone here, and I would say that is RLHF,
which currently does work a bit better than SFT, if you can get it to work.
But again, this is pretty involved, I would say.
And to optimize your costs, try to explore,
look for lower capacity models, or shorter prompts, and so on.
I also wanted to say a few words about the use cases,
in which I think LLMs are currently well-suited for.
So in particular, note that there's a large number of limitations to LLMs today.
And so I would keep that definitely in mind for all your applications.
Models, and this, by the way, could be an entire talk,
so I don't have time to cover it in full detail.
Models may be biased, they may fabricate, hallucinate information.
They may have reasoning errors.
They may struggle.
LLMs can run entire classes of applications.
They have knowledge cut-offs,
so they might not know any information above, say, September 2021.
They are susceptible to a large range of attacks,
which are sort of like coming out on Twitter daily,
including prompt injection, jailbreak attacks, data poisoning attacks, and so on.
So my recommendation right now is use LLMs in low-stakes applications,
combine them with always with human oversight,
use them as a source of inspiration and suggestions,
and think co-pilots instead of completely autonomous agents,
that are just like performing a task somewhere.
It's just not clear that the models are there right now.
So I wanted to close by saying that GPT-4 is an amazing artifact.
I'm very thankful that it exists.
And it's beautiful.
It has a ton of knowledge across so many areas.
It can do math, code, and so on.
And in addition, there's this thriving ecosystem of everything else
that is being built and incorporated into the ecosystem.
Some of these things I've talked about.
And all of this power is accessible at your fingertips.
So here's everything that's needed in terms of code
to ask GPT-4 a question, to prompt it, and get a response.
In this case, I said,
can you say something to inspire the audience of Microsoft Build 2023?
And I just punched this into Python, and verbatim, GPT-4 said the following.
And by the way, I did not know that they used this trick in the keynote.
So I thought I was being clever, but it is really good at this.
It says, ladies and gentlemen, innovators and trailblazers, Microsoft.
Build 2023.
Welcome to the gathering of brilliant minds like no other.
You are the architects of the future,
the visionaries molding the digital realm in which humanity thrives.
Embrace the limitless possibilities of technologies
and let your ideas soar as high as your imagination.
Together, let's create a more connected, remarkable,
and inclusive world for generations to come.
Get ready to unleash your creativity,
canvass the unknown, and turn dreams into reality.
Your journey begins today.
www.microsoft.com