Hi everyone. So today we are once again continuing our implementation of MakeMore.
Now so far we've come up to here, multilayer perceptrons, and our neural net looked like this,
and we were implementing this over the last few lectures. Now I'm sure everyone is very excited
to go into recurrent neural networks and all of their variants and how they work, and the diagrams
look cool and it's very exciting and interesting, and we're going to get a better result.
But unfortunately I think we have to remain here for one more lecture. And the reason for that is
we've already trained this multilayer perceptron, right, and we are getting pretty good loss,
and I think we have a pretty decent understanding of the architecture and how it works.
But the line of code here that I take an issue with is here, loss.backward. That is, we are
taking PyTorch autograd and using it to calculate all of our gradients along the way. And I would
like to remove the use of loss.backward, and I would like us to write our backward pass manually
on the level of tensors. And I think that this is a very useful exercise for the following reasons.
I actually have an entire blog post on this topic, but I'd like to call backpropagation a leaky
abstraction. And what I mean by that is backpropagation doesn't just make your neural
networks just work magically. It's not the case that you can just stack up arbitrary Lego blocks
of differentiable functions and just cross your fingers and backpropagate and everything is great.
Things don't just work automatically. It is a leaky abstraction in the sense that
you can shoot yourself in the foot if you do not understand its internals. It will magically not
work or not work optimally. And you will need to understand how it works under the hood if you're
hoping to debug it and if you are hoping to address it in your neural net. So this blog post
here from a while ago goes into some of those examples. So for example, we've already covered
them, some of them already. For example, the flat tails of these functions and how you do not want
to saturate them too much because your gradients will die. The case of dead neurons, which I've
already covered as well. The case of exploding or
exploding gradients in the case of recurring neural networks, which we are about to cover.
And then also you will often come across some examples in the wild. This is a snippet that I
found in a random code base on the internet where they actually have like a very subtle but pretty
major bug in their implementation. And the bug points at the fact that the author of this code
does not actually understand backpropagation. So what they're trying to do here is they're trying
to clip the loss at a certain maximum value. But actually what they're trying to do is they're
trying to clip the gradients to have a maximum value instead of trying to clip the loss at a
maximum value. And indirectly, they're basically causing some of the outliers to be actually
ignored. Because when you clip the loss of an outlier, you are setting its gradient to 0.
And so have a look through this and read through it. But there's basically a bunch of subtle
issues that you're going to avoid if you actually know what you're doing. And that's why I don't
think it's the case that because PyTorch or other frameworks offer autograd, it is okay for us to do.
ignore how it works. Now, we've actually already covered autograd and we wrote micrograd, but
micrograd was an autograd engine only on the level of individual scalars. So the atoms were single
individual numbers. And, you know, I don't think it's enough. And I'd like us to basically think
about backpropagation on the level of tensors as well. And so in a summary, I think it's a good
exercise. I think it is very, very valuable. You're going to become better at debugging neural
networks and making sure that you understand what you're doing. It is going to make everything
fully explicit. So you're not going to be nervous about what is hidden away from you. And basically
in general, we're going to emerge stronger. And so let's get into it. A bit of a fun historical note
here is that today writing your backward pass by hand and manually is not recommended and no one
does it except for the purposes of exercise. But about 10 years ago in deep learning, this was
fairly standard and in fact pervasive. So at the time, everyone used to write their backward pass
by hand manually.
Including myself. And it's just what you would do. So we used to write backward pass by hand. And now
everyone just calls lost that backward. We've lost something. I want to give you a few examples of
this. So here's a 2006 paper from Jeff Hinton and Ruslan Slakhtinov in science that was
influential at the time. And this was training some architectures called restricted Boltzmann
machines. And basically, it's an autoencoder trained here. And this is from roughly
2000.
In 2010, I had a library for training restricted Boltzmann machines. And this was at the time
written in Matlab. So Python was not used for deep learning pervasively. It was all Matlab. And
Matlab was this scientific computing package that everyone would use. So we would write Matlab,
which is barely a programming language as well. But it had a very convenient tensor class.
And it was this computing environment and you would run here. It would all run on the CPU,
of course. But you would have very nice plots to go with it and a built-in debugger. And it was
pretty nice. Now, the code in this package in 2010 that I wrote for fitting restricted Boltzmann
machines to a large extent is recognizable. But I wanted to show you how you would... Well,
I'm creating the data in the XY batches. I'm initializing the neural net. So it's got weights
and biases just like we're used to. And then this is the training loop where we actually do the
forward pass. And then here, at this time, they didn't even necessarily use back propagation to
train neural networks. So this, in particular, implements a lot of the training that we're doing.
It implements contrastive divergence, which estimates a gradient. And then here, we take
that gradient and use it for a parameter update along the lines that we're used to. Yeah, here.
But you can see that basically people are meddling with these gradients directly and inline and
themselves. It wasn't that common to use an autograd engine. Here's one more example from a
paper of mine from 2014 called Deep Fragment Embeddings. And here, what I was doing is I was
aligning images and text.
And here, I'm implementing the cost function. And it was standard to implement not just the cost,
but also the backward pass manually. So here, I'm calculating the image embeddings,
and I'm implementing the cost function. And here, I'm implementing the backward pass manually.
Sentence embeddings, I calculate the scores. This is the loss function. And then once I have
the loss function, I do the backward pass right here. So I backward through the loss function
and through the neural net, and I append regularization. So everything was done by hand
manually, and you would just write out the backward pass. And then you would use a gradient
checker to make sure that your numerical estimate of the gradient agrees with the one you calculated
during back propagation. So this was very standard for a long time. But today, of course, it is
standard to use an autograd engine. But it was definitely useful, and I think people sort of
understood how these neural networks work on a very intuitive level. And so I think it's a good
exercise again, and this is where we want to be. Okay, so just as a reminder from our previous
lecture, this is the Jupyter notebook that we implemented at the time. And we're going to keep
everything the same. So we're still going to have a two-layer multi-layer perceptron with a batch
normalization layer. So the forward pass will be basically identical to this lecture. But here,
we're going to get rid of loss.backward. And instead, we're going to
write the backward pass manually. Now, here's the starter code for this lecture. We are becoming
a backprop ninja in this notebook. And the first few cells here are identical to what we are used
to. So we are doing some imports, loading in the data set, and processing the data set. None of
this changed. Now, here, I'm introducing a utility function that we're going to use later to compare
the gradients. So in particular, we are going to have the gradients that we estimate manually
ourselves. And we're going to have gradients that PyTorch calculates. And we're going to be
checking for correctness, assuming, of course, that PyTorch is correct.
Then here, we have the initialization that we are quite used to. So we have our embedding table for
the characters, the first layer, second layer, and a batch normalization in between. And here's
where we create all the parameters. Now, you will note that I changed the initialization a little
bit to be small numbers. So normally, you would set the biases to be all zero. Here, I'm setting
them to be small random numbers. And I'm doing this because if your variables are all zero,
or initialized to exactly zero, sometimes what can happen is that can mask an incorrect
implementation of a gradient. Because when everything is zero, it sort of like simplifies
and gives you a much simpler expression of the gradient than you would otherwise get. And so by
making it small numbers, I'm trying to unmask those potential errors in these calculations.
You also notice that I'm using b1 in the first layer. I'm using a bias despite batch
normalization right afterwards. So this would typically not be what you'd do because we talked
about the bias. So I'm going to mask the bias. And I'm going to mask the bias. And I'm going to
fact that you don't need a bias but i'm doing this here just for fun because we're going to
have a gradient with respect to it and we can check that we are still calculating it correctly
even though this bias is spurious so here i'm calculating a single batch and then here i am
doing a forward pass now you'll notice that the forward pass is significantly expanded from what
we are used to here the forward pass was just um here now the reason that the forward pass is
longer is for two reasons number one here we just had an f dot cross entropy but here i am bringing
back a explicit implementation of the loss function and number two i've broken up the
implementation into manageable chunks so we have a lot a lot more intermediate tensors along the way
in the forward pass and that's because we are about to go backwards and calculate the gradients
in this back propagation from the bottom to the top so we're going to go upwards and just like we
have for example the lockpick
props tensor in a forward pass in a backward pass we're going to have a d lock props which is going
to store the derivative of the loss with respect to the lock props tensor and so we're going to
be prepending d to every one of these tensors and calculating it along the way of this back
propagation so as an example we have a b in raw here we're going to be calculating a db in raw
so here i'm telling pytorch that we want to retain the grad of all these intermediate values because
here in exercise one we're going to calculate the backward pass
so we're going to calculate all these d variable d variables and use the cmp function i've introduced
above to check our correctness with respect to what pytorch is telling us this is going to be
exercise one where we sort of back propagate through this entire graph now just to give you
a very quick preview of what's going to happen in exercise two and below
here we have fully broken up the loss and back propagated through it manually in all
the little atomic pieces that make it up but here we're going to collapse the loss into
a single cross entropy call and instead we're going to analytically derive using
math and paper and pencil the gradient of the loss with respect to the logits and instead of
back propagating through all of its little chunks one at a time we're just going to analytically
derive what that gradient is and we're going to implement that which is much more efficient as
we'll see in a bit then we're going to do the exact same thing for batch normalization so
instead of breaking up bastion arm into all the little tiny components we're going to use pen and
paper and mathematics and calculus to derive the gradient through the bachelor bathroom layer so
we're going to calculate the backward pass through bathroom layer in a much more efficient expression
instead of backward propagating through all of its little pieces independently
so it's going to be exercise three and then in exercise four we're going to put it all together
and this is the full code of training this two layer mlp and we're going to basically insert
our manual backdrop and we're going to take out lost up backward and you will basically see
that you can get all the same results using fully your own code and the only thing we're using from
pytorch is the torch.tensor to make the calculations efficient but otherwise you will understand fully
what it means to forward and backward the neural net and train it and i think that'll be awesome so
let's get to it okay so i ran all the cells of this notebook all the way up to here and i'm going
to erase this and i'm going to start implementing backward pass starting with d lock probes so we
go here to calculate the gradient of the loss with respect to all the elements of the lock props
tensor now i'm going to give away the answer here but i wanted to put a quick note here that
i think would be most pedagogically useful for you is to actually go into the description of this
video and find the link to this jupyter notebook you can find it both on github but you can also
find google collab with it so you don't have to install anything you'll just go to a website on
google collab and you can try to implement these derivatives or gradients yourself and then if you
are not able to come to my video and see me do it and so work in tandem and try it first yourself
and then see me give away the answer and i think that'll be most valuable to you and that's how i
recommend you go through this lecture so we are starting here with d log props now d log props
will hold the derivative of the loss with respect to all the elements of log props what is inside
log blobs the shape of this is 32 by 27. so it's not going to surprise you that d log props should
also be an array of size 32 by 27 because we want the derivative loss with respect to all of its
elements so the sizes of those are always going to be equal now how how does log probes influence
the loss okay loss is negative log probes indexed with range of n and yb and then the mean of that
now just as a reminder yb is just basically an array of all the
correct indexes of all the indexes of all the indexes of all the indexes of all the indexes of
all the indexes so what we're doing here is we're taking the log props array of size 32 by 27
right and then we are going in every single row and in each row we are plugging plucking out
the index 8 and then 14 and 15 and so on so we're going down the rows
that's the iterator range of n and then we are always plucking out the index and the
column specified by this tensor yb so in the zeroth row we are taking the eighth column
in the first row we're taking the 14th column etc and so log props at this plucks out all those
log probabilities of the correct next character in a sequence so that's what that does and the
shape of this or the size of it is of course 32 because our batch size is 32. so these elements
get plucked out and then their mean and the negative of that becomes loss so i always like to
examples to understand the numerical form of derivative what's going on here is once we've
plucked out these examples um we're taking the mean and then the negative so the loss basically
if i can write it this way is the negative of say a plus b plus c
and the mean of those three numbers would be say negative would divide three that would be how we
achieve the mean of three numbers a b c although we actually have 32 numbers here and so what is
loss by say like da right well if we simplify this expression mathematically this is negative
one over three of a and negative one plus negative one over three of b
plus negative one over three of c and so what is d loss by d a it's just negative one over three
and so you can see that if we don't just have a b and c but we have 32 numbers
then d loss by d um you know every one of those numbers is going to be one over n more generally
the size of the batch, 32 in this case.
So DLoss by DLockProbs is negative one over N
in all these places.
Now, what about the other elements inside LockProbs?
Because LockProbs is a large array.
You see that LockProbs.shape is 32 by 27,
but only 32 of them participate in the loss calculation.
So what's the derivative of all the other,
most of the elements that do not get blocked out here?
Well, their loss intuitively is zero.
Sorry, their gradient intuitively is zero.
And that's because they did not participate in the loss.
So most of these numbers inside this tensor
does not feed into the loss.
And so if we were to change these numbers,
then the loss doesn't change,
which is the equivalent of what I was saying,
that the derivative of the loss with respect to them is zero.
They don't impact it.
So here's a way to implement this derivative then.
We start out with Torch.zeros of shape 32.
So we're going to set it to 32 by 27,
or let's just say instead of doing this because we don't want to hard-code numbers,
let's do Torch.zeros like LockProbs.
So basically this is going to create an array of zeros exactly in the shape of LockProbs.
And then we need to set the derivative of negative one over n inside exactly these locations.
So here's what we can do.
The LockProbs indexed in the identical way
will be just set to negative one over zero divide n.
Right, just like we derived here.
So now let me erase all of these reasoning.
And then this is the candidate derivative for DLockProbs.
Let's uncomment the first line and check that this is correct.
Okay, so CMP ran, and let's go back to CMP.
And you see that what it's doing is it's calculating if
the calculated value by us, which is dt,
is exactly equal to t.grad as calculated by PyTorch.
And then this is making sure that all of the elements are exactly equal.
And then converting this to a single Boolean value
because we don't want a Boolean tensor, we just want a Boolean value.
And then here we are making sure that, okay, if they're not exactly equal,
maybe they are approximately equal because of some floating point issues.
But they're very, very close.
So here we are using Torch.allClose, which has a little bit of a wiggle available
because sometimes you can get very, very close.
But if you use a slightly different calculation,
because of floating point, you can't get very, very close.
because of floating point arithmetic, you can get a slightly different result.
So this is checking if you get an approximately close result.
And then here we are checking the maximum, basically the value that has the highest difference,
and what is the difference, and the absolute value difference between those two.
And so we are printing whether we have an exact equality, an approximate equality,
and what is the largest difference.
And so here we see that we actually have exact equality.
And so therefore, of course, we also have an approximate equality,
and the maximum difference is exactly zero.
So basically, our DLOGPROPS is exactly equal to what PyTorch calculated to be
logPROPS.grad in its backpropagation.
So, so far, we're doing pretty well.
Okay, so let's now continue our backpropagation.
We have that logPROPS depends on PROPS through a log.
So all the elements of PROPS are being element-wise applied log to.
Now, if we want DPROPS...
then, then remember your micrograph training.
We have like a log node.
It takes in PROPS and creates logPROPS.
And DPROPS will be the local derivative of that individual operation, log,
times the derivative loss with respect to its output, which in this case is DLOGPROPS.
So what is the local derivative of this operation?
Well, we are taking log element-wise, and we can come here and we can see,
well, from alpha is your friend, that d by dx of log of x is just simply 1 over x.
So therefore, in this case, x is PROPS.
So we have d by dx is 1 over x, which is 1 over PROPS.
And then this is the local derivative.
And then times, we want to chain it.
So this is chain rule.
Times DLOGPROPS.
Then let me uncomment this and let me run the cell in place.
And we see that the derivative of PROPS as we calculated here is exactly correct.
And so notice here how this works.
PROPS that are...
PROPS is going to be inverted and then element-wise,
and then element-wise, multiplied here.
So if your PROPS is very, very close to 1,
that means your network is currently predicting the character correctly,
then this will become 1 over 1, and DLOGPROPS just gets passed through.
But if your probabilities are incorrectly assigned,
so if the correct character here is getting a very low probability,
then 1.0 dividing by it will boost this and then multiply by DLOGPROPS.
So basically, what this line is doing intuitively is it's taking
the...
the examples that have a very low probability currently assigned,
and it's boosting their gradient.
You can look at it that way.
Next up is COUNTSUMINV.
So we want the derivative of this.
Now, let me just pause here and kind of introduce what's happening here in general,
because I know it's a little bit confusing.
We have the logits that come out of the neural net.
Here, what I'm doing is I'm finding the maximum in each row,
and I'm subtracting it for the purpose of numerical stability.
And we talked about how...
if you do not do this,
you run into numerical issues if some of the logits take on two large values
because we end up exponentiating them.
So this is done just for safety, numerically.
Then here's the exponentiation of all the sort of logits to create our counts.
And then we want to take the sum of these counts and normalize
so that all of the probes sum to 1.
Now here, instead of using 1 over COUNTSUM,
I use raised to the power of negative 1.
Mathematically, they are identical.
I just found that there's something wrong with the PyTorch implementation
of the backward pass of division, and it gives like a weird result,
but that doesn't happen for star star negative 1,
so I'm using this formula instead.
But basically, all that's happening here is we got the logits,
we want to exponentiate all of them,
and we want to normalize the counts to create our probabilities.
It's just that it's happening across multiple lines.
So now, here,
we want to normalize the counts to create our probabilities.
We want to first take the derivative,
we want to backpropagate into COUNTSUM and then into COUNTS as well.
So what should be the COUNTSUM?
Now, we actually have to be careful here
because we have to scrutinize and be careful with the shapes.
So COUNTS.shape and then COUNTSUM.inv.shape are different.
So in particular, COUNTS is 32 by 27,
but this COUNTSUM.inv is 32 by 1.
And so in this multiplication here,
we also have an implicit broadcasting that PyTorch will do
because it needs to take this column tensor of 32 numbers
and replicate it horizontally 27 times to align these two tensors
so it can do an element-wise multiply.
So really what this looks like is the following,
using a toy example again.
What we really have here is just props is COUNTS times COUNTSUM.inv.
So it's C equals A times B.
But A is 3 by 3, and B is just 3 by 1, a column tensor.
And so PyTorch internally
replicated these elements of B,
and it did that across all the columns.
So for example, B1, which is the first element of B,
would be replicated here across all the columns in this multiplication.
And now we're trying to backpropagate through this operation to COUNTSUM.inv.
So when we are calculating this derivative,
it's important to realize that this looks like a single operation,
but actually is two operations applied sequentially.
The first operation that PyTorch did is it took
this column tensor and replicated it across all the columns,
basically 27 times.
So that's the first operation, it's a replication.
And then the second operation is the multiplication.
So let's first backprop through the multiplication.
If these two arrays were of the same size,
and we just have A and B, both of them 3 by 3,
then how do we backpropagate through a multiplication?
So if we just have scalars and not tensors,
then if you have C equals A times B,
then what is the derivative of C with respect to B?
Well, it's just A.
And so that's the local derivative.
So here in our case, undoing the multiplication
and backpropagating through just the multiplication itself,
which is element-wise, is going to be the local derivative,
which in this case is simply COUNTS,
because COUNTS is the A.
So this is the local derivative, and then times,
because of the chain rule, dprops.
So this here is the dprops.
So this is the local derivative, or the gradient,
but with respect to replicated B.
But we don't have a replicated B,
we just have a single B column.
So how do we now backpropagate through the replication?
And intuitively, this B1 is the same variable,
and it's just reused multiple times.
And so you can look at it as being equivalent
to a case we've encountered in micrograd.
And so here I'm just pulling out a random graph
we used in micrograd.
We had an example where a single node,
has its output feeding into two branches
of basically the graph until the last function.
And we're talking about how the correct thing to do
in the backward pass is we need to sum all the gradients
that arrive at any one node.
So across these different branches,
the gradients would sum.
So if a node is used multiple times,
the gradients for all of its uses sum during backpropagation.
So here, B1 is used multiple times in all these columns,
and therefore the right thing to do here is to sum
horizontally across all the rows.
So we want to sum in dimension 1,
but we want to retain this dimension
so that the countSumInv and its gradient
are going to be exactly the same shape.
So we want to make sure that we keep them as true
so we don't lose this dimension.
And this will make the countSumInv
be exactly shaped 32 by 1.
So revealing this comparison as well and running this,
we see that we get an exact match.
So this derivative is exactly correct.
And let me erase this.
Now let's also backpropagate into counts,
which is the other variable here to create props.
So from props to countSumInv,
we just did that.
Let's go into counts as well.
So dCounts is our A.
So dC by dA is just B.
So therefore it's countSumInv.
And then times, chain rule, dProps.
Now countSumInv is 32 by 1.
dProps is 32 by 27.
So those will broadcast fine
and will give us dCounts.
There's no additional summation required here.
There will be a broadcasting
that happens in this multiply here
because countSumInv needs to be replicated again
to correctly multiply dProps.
But that's going to give the correct result.
So as far as this single operation is concerned.
So we've backpropagated from props to counts,
but we can't actually check the derivative of counts.
I have it much later on.
And the reason for that is because
countSumInv depends on counts.
And so there's a second branch here
that we have to finish.
Because countSumInv backpropagates into countSum,
and countSum will backpropagate into counts.
And so counts is a node that is being used twice.
It's used right here in two props,
and it goes through this other branch
through countSumInv.
So even though we've calculated
the first contribution of it,
we still have to calculate the second contribution of it later.
Okay, so we're continuing with this branch.
We have the derivative for countSumInv.
Now we want the derivative for countSum.
So dCountSum equals
what is the local derivative of this operation?
So this is basically an element-wise
1 over countsSum.
So countSum raised to the power of negative 1
is the same as 1 over countsSum.
If we go to wall from alpha,
we see that x to the negative 1,
d by dx of it,
is basically negative x to the negative 2.
Negative 1 over s squared
is the same as negative x to the negative 2.
So dCountSum here will be
local derivative is going to be
negative countsSum to the negative 2,
that's the local derivative,
times chain rule, which is
countSumInv.
So that's dCountSum.
Let's uncomment this
and check that I am correct.
Okay, so we have perfect equality.
And there's no sketchiness going on here
with any shapes because these are of the same shape.
Okay, next up we want to
backpropagate through this line.
We have that countSum is counts.sum
along the rows.
So I wrote out some help here.
We have to keep in mind that
counts, of course, is 32 by 27.
And countsSum is 32 by 1.
So in this backpropagation,
we need to take this column of derivatives
and transform it into an array of derivatives,
two-dimensional array.
So what is this operation doing?
We're taking some kind of an input,
like, say, a 3x3 matrix A,
and we are summing up the rows
into a column tensor B.
B1, B2, B3, that is basically this.
So now we have the derivatives
of the loss with respect to B.
And now we have the elements of B.
And now we want the derivative of the loss
with respect to all these little a's.
So how do the b's depend on the a's,
is basically what we're after.
What is the local derivative of this operation?
Well, we can see here that B1
only depends on these elements here.
The derivative of B1
with respect to all of these elements down here
is 0.
But for these elements here,
like A11, A12, etc.,
the local derivative is 1, right?
So dB1 by dA11, for example, is 1.
So it's 1, 1, and 1.
So when we have the derivative of the loss
with respect to B1,
the local derivative of B1
with respect to these inputs is 0 here,
but it's 1 on these guys.
So in the chain rule,
we have the local derivative
times the derivative of B1.
And so because the local derivative
is 1 on these three elements,
the local derivative of multiplying
the derivative of B1
will just be the derivative of B1.
And so you can look at it as a router.
Basically, an addition
is a router of gradient.
Whatever gradient comes from above,
it just gets routed equally
to all the elements that participate
in that addition.
So in this case, the derivative of B1
will just flow equally to the derivative
of A11, A12, and A13.
So if we have a derivative
of all the elements of B
in this column tensor,
which we calculated just now,
we basically see that what that amounts to
is all of these are now flowing
to all these elements of A,
and they're doing that horizontally.
So basically what we want
is we want to take the decount sum
of size 32 by 1,
and we just want to replicate it
27 times horizontally
to create 32 by 27 array.
So there's many ways to implement this operation.
You could, of course, just replicate the tensor,
but I think maybe one clean one
is that decounts is simply
torch.once-like,
so just two-dimensional arrays
of once in the shape of counts,
so 32 by 27,
times decounts sum.
So this way we're letting
the broadcasting here
basically implement the replication.
You can look at it that way.
But then we have to also be careful
because decounts
was all already calculated.
We calculated earlier here,
and that was just the first branch,
and we're now finishing the second branch.
So we need to make sure that these gradients add,
so plus equals.
And then here,
let's comment out
the comparison,
and let's make sure, crossing fingers,
that we have the correct result.
So PyTorch agrees with us
on this gradient as well.
Okay, hopefully we're getting a hang of this now.
Counts is an element-wise exp
of norm logits.
So now we want dNormLogits,
and because it's an element-wise operation,
everything is very simple.
It's the local derivative of e to the x.
It's famously just e to the x.
So this is the local derivative.
That is the local derivative.
Now we already calculated it,
and it's inside counts.
So we may as well potentially just reuse counts.
That is the local derivative.
Times dCounts.
Funny as that looks.
Counts times dCounts is dNormLogits.
And now let's erase this,
and let's verify,
and let's go.
So that's dNormLogits.
Okay, so we are here
on this line now, dNormLogits.
We have that,
and we're trying to calculate dLogits
and dLogitMaxes.
So back-propagating through this line.
Now we have to be careful here,
because the shapes, again, are not the same,
and so there's an implicit broadcasting happening here.
So dNormLogits has the shape 32x27.
dLogits does as well,
but dLogitMaxes is only 32x1.
So there's a broadcast
here in the minus.
Now here I tried to
sort of write out a toy example again.
We basically have that
this is our c equals a minus b,
and we see that because of the shape,
these are 3x3, but this one is just a column.
And so for example,
every element of c,
we have to look at how it came to be.
And every element of c is just
the corresponding element of a minus
basically that associated b.
So it's very clear now
that the derivatives of
every one of these c's with respect to their inputs
are 1
for the corresponding a,
and it's a negative 1
for the corresponding b.
And so therefore,
the derivatives
on the c will flow
equally to the corresponding a's,
and then also to the corresponding b's.
But then in addition to that,
the b's are broadcast,
so we'll have to do the additional sum
just like we did before.
And of course, the derivatives for b's
will undergo a minus,
because the local derivative here
is negative 1.
So dc32 by db3 is negative 1.
So let's just implement that.
Basically, dlogits will be
exactly copying
the derivative on normlogits.
So
dlogits equals
dnormlogits, and I'll do a .clone
for safety, so we're just making a copy.
And then we have that
dlogitmaxis,
will be the negative
of dnormlogits,
because of the negative sign.
And then we have to be careful because
dlogitmaxis is
a column, and so
just like we saw before,
because we keep replicating the same
elements across all the
columns, then in the
backward pass, because we keep reusing
this, these are all just like separate
branches of use of that one variable.
And so therefore, we have to do a
sum along 1, we'd keep
them equals true, so that we don't
destroy this dimension.
And then dlogitmaxis will be the same
shape. Now we have to be careful because
this dlogits is not the final dlogits,
and that's because
not only do we get gradient signal
into logits through here, but
logitmaxis is a function of logits,
and that's a second branch into
logits. So this is not yet our final
derivative for logits, we will come back
later for the second branch.
For now, dlogitmaxis is the final derivative,
so let me uncomment this
cmp here, and let's just run this.
And logitmaxis,
if pytorch, agrees
with us. So that was the derivative
into, through
this line. Now before
we move on, I want to pause here briefly,
and I want to look at these logitmaxis, and
especially their gradients. We've
talked previously in the previous lecture
that the only reason we're doing this is
for the numerical stability of the softmax
that we are implementing here.
And we talked about how if you take
these logits for any one of these examples,
so one row of this logits tensor,
if you add or subtract
any value equally to all the elements,
then the value
of the probes will be unchanged.
You're not changing the softmax. The only thing
that this is doing is it's making sure that
exp doesn't overflow. And the
reason we're using a max is because then we
are guaranteed that each row of logits,
the highest number, is zero.
And so this will be safe.
And so
basically
that has repercussions.
If it is the case that changing
logitmaxis does not change the
probes, and therefore does not change the loss,
then the gradient on logitmaxis
should be zero.
Because saying those two things is the same.
So indeed we hope that this is
very, very small numbers. Indeed we hope this is zero.
Now because of floating
point sort of wonkiness,
this doesn't come out exactly zero.
Only in some of the rows it does.
But we get extremely small values, like
1e-9 or 10.
And so this is telling us that the values of
logitmaxis are not impacting the loss
as they shouldn't.
It feels kind of weird to backpropagate through this branch,
honestly, because
if you have any
implementation of f.crossentropy and
pytorch, and you block together
all of these elements, and you're not doing backpropagation
piece by piece, then you would
probably assume that the derivative
through here is exactly zero.
So you would be sort of
skipping
this branch. Because
it's only done for numerical stability.
But it's interesting to see that even if you break up
everything into the full atoms, and you
still do the computation as you'd like
with respect to numerical stability, the correct thing
happens. And you still get
very, very small gradients here.
Basically reflecting the fact that
the values of these do not matter
with respect to the final loss.
Okay, so let's now continue backpropagation
through this line here.
We've just calculated the logitmaxis, and now
we want to backprop into logits through this
second branch. Now here of course
we took logits, and we took the max
along all the rows, and then
we looked at its values here.
Now the way this works is that in pytorch,
this thing here,
the max returns both the values,
and it returns the indices at which those
values to count the maximum value.
Now in the forward pass, we only
used values, because that's all we needed.
But in the backward pass, it's extremely
useful to know about where those
maximum values occurred.
And we have the indices at which they occurred.
And this will of course help us do
the backpropagation.
Because what should the backward pass be
here in this case? We have the logit tensor,
which is 32 by 27, and
in each row we find the maximum value,
and then that value gets plucked out into
logitmaxis. And so intuitively,
basically
the derivative
flowing through here then
should be 1
times the local derivative
is 1 for the appropriate entry that was
plucked out, and
then times the global derivative,
of the logitmaxis.
So really what we're doing here, if you think through it,
is we need to take the delogitmaxis,
and we need to scatter it to
the correct positions
in these logits,
from where the maximum values came.
And so,
I came up with
one line of code that does that.
Let me just erase a bunch of stuff here.
You could do it kind of very similar
to what we've done here, where we create
a zeros, and then we populate
the correct elements.
So we use the indices here, and we would
set them to be 1. But you can
also use one hot.
So f dot one hot,
and then I'm taking the logits of max
over the first dimension
dot indices, and I'm telling
PyTorch that
the dimension of
every one of these tensors should be
27.
And so what this is going to do
is...
Okay, I apologize, this is crazy.
PLT dot imchev of this.
It's really just an array
of where the maxes came from
in each row, and that element is 1,
and all the other elements are 0.
So it's one hot vector in each row,
and these indices are now populating
a single 1 in the proper
place. And then what I'm doing
here is I'm multiplying by the logit
maxes. And keep in mind that
this is a column
of 32 by 1.
And so when I'm doing this
times the logit maxes,
the logit maxes will broadcast
and that column will get replicated,
and then element-wise multiply
will ensure that each of these
just gets routed to whichever
one of these bits is turned on.
And so that's another way to implement
this kind of
operation, and
both of these can be used. I just
thought I would show an equivalent way to do it.
And I'm using plus equals because
we already calculated the logits here,
and this is now the second branch.
So let's
look at logits and make sure that
this is correct.
And we see that we have exactly the correct answer.
Next up,
we want to continue with logits here.
That is an outcome of a matrix
multiplication and a bias offset
in this linear layer.
So I've
printed out the shapes of all these intermediate
tensors. We see that logits
is of course 32 by 27, as we've just
seen. Then the
h here is 32 by 64.
So these are 64-dimensional hidden states.
And then this w
matrix projects those 64-dimensional
vectors into 27 dimensions.
And then there's a 27-dimensional
offset, which is a
one-dimensional vector. Now we
should note that this plus here actually
broadcasts, because h multiplied
by w2
will give us a 32 by 27.
And so then this plus
b2 is a 27-dimensional
vector here. Now in the
rules of broadcasting, what's going to happen with this bias
vector is that this one-dimensional
vector of 27 will get a lot
aligned with an padded dimension
of 1 on the left.
And it will basically become a row vector,
and then it will get replicated
vertically 32 times to make it
32 by 27, and then there's an element-wise
multiply.
Now the question
is how do we backpropagate from
logits to the hidden states,
the weight matrix w2, and the bias
b2? And you might
think that we need to go to some
matrix calculus,
and then we have to look up the derivative
for matrix multiplication,
but actually you don't have to do any of that, and you can go
back to first principles and derive this yourself
on a piece of paper.
And specifically what I like to do, and what
I find works well for me, is you find
a specific small example
that you then fully write out, and then
in the process of analyzing how that individual
small example works, you will understand
the broader pattern, and you'll be able to generalize
and write out the full
general formula for
how these derivatives flow in an expression
like this. So let's try that out.
So pardon the low-budget production
here, but what I've done here
is I'm writing it out on a piece of paper.
Really what we are interested in is we have
a multiply b plus c,
and that creates a d.
And we have the derivative
of the loss with respect to d, and we'd like to
know what the derivative of the loss is with respect to a, b,
and c. Now these
here are little two-dimensional examples
of matrix multiplication.
2 by 2 times a 2 by 2,
plus a 2,
a vector of just two elements, c1 and c2,
gives me a 2 by 2.
Now notice here that
I have a bias vector
here called c, and the
bias vector is c1 and c2, but
as I described over here, that bias
vector will become a row vector in the broadcasting,
and will replicate vertically.
So that's what's happening here as well. c1, c2
is replicated vertically,
and we see how we have two rows of c1,
c2 as a result.
So now when I say write it out,
I just mean like this.
Basically break up this matrix multiplication
into the actual thing that's
going on under the hood.
So as a result of matrix multiplication
and how it works, d11
is the result of a dot product between the
first row of a and the first column
of b. So a11, b11,
plus a12, b21,
plus c1.
And so on
and so forth for all the other elements of d.
And once you actually write
it out, it becomes obvious that it's just a bunch of
multiplies and adds.
And we know from micrograd
how to differentiate multiplies and adds.
And so this is not scary anymore.
It's not just matrix multiplication.
It's just tedious, unfortunately.
But this is completely tractable.
We have dl by d for all of these,
and we want dl by
all these little other variables.
So how do we achieve that, and how do we
actually get the gradients?
Okay, so the low-budget production continues here.
So let's, for example, derive
the derivative of the loss with respect to
a11.
We see here that a11 occurs twice
in our simple expression, right here, right here,
and influences d11 and d12.
So this is, so what
is dl by d a11?
Well, it's dl by d11
times
the local derivative of d11,
which in this case is just b11,
because that's what's multiplying
a11 here.
And likewise here, the local
derivative of d12 with respect to a11
is just b12.
And so b12 will, in the chain rule, therefore,
multiply dl by d12.
And then, because a11
is used both to produce
d11 and d12, we need
to add up the contributions
of both of those sort of
chains that are running in parallel.
And that's why we get a plus, just
adding up those two,
those two contributions. And that gives
us dl by d a11.
We can do the exact same analysis for
the other one, for all the other
elements of a. And when you
simply write it out, it's just super
simple taking of
gradients on, you know,
expressions like this.
You find that
this matrix, dl by d a,
that we're after, right, if we
just arrange all of them in the
same shape as a takes, so
a is just a 2x2 matrix, so
dl by d a here will be
also just the same
shape
tensor with the derivatives
now. So dl by d a11
etc. And we see that actually
we can express what we've written out here
as a matrix multiply.
And so it just so
happens that dl by, that all
of these formulas that we've derived here
by taking gradients can actually
be expressed as a matrix multiplication.
And in particular, we see that it is the matrix
multiplication of these two
matrices. So it
is the dl
by d and then matrix
multiplying b, but b
transpose, actually. So you see that
b21 and b12
have changed place,
whereas before we had, of course,
b11, b12, b21,
b22. So you see that
this other matrix, b,
is transposed. And so
basically what we have, long story short, just by
doing very simple reasoning here,
by breaking up the expression in the case of
a very simple example, is that
dl by d a is
which is this, is simply
equal to dl by dd matrix
multiplied with b transpose.
So that
is what we have so far.
Now, we also want the derivative with respect to
b and c.
Now, for
b, I'm not actually doing the full derivation
because, honestly, it's
not deep. It's just
annoying. It's exhausting. You can
actually do this analysis yourself. You'll
also find that if you take these expressions
and you differentiate with respect to b
instead of a, you will find that
dl by db is also a matrix
multiplication. In this case, you have to take
the matrix a and transpose
it and matrix multiply that with
dl by dd.
And that's what gives you dl by db.
And then here for
the offsets, c1 and
c2, if you again just differentiate
with respect to c1, you will find
an expression like this.
And c2, an expression
like this. And basically
you'll find that dl by dc is
simply, because they're just offsetting
these expressions, you just have to take
the dl by dd matrix
of the derivatives of d
and you just have to
sum across the columns.
And that gives you the derivatives
for c.
So, long story short,
the backward pass of a matrix
multiply is a matrix multiply.
And instead of, just like we had
d equals a times b plus c,
in a scalar case,
we sort of arrive at something very, very similar
but now with a matrix multiplication
instead of a scalar multiplication.
So, the derivative
of d with respect
to a is
dl by dd
matrix multiply b transpose
and here it's a transpose
multiply dl by dd. But in both
cases it's a matrix multiplication with
the derivative and
the other term in the
multiplication. And
for c it is a sum.
Now, I'll tell you a secret.
I can never remember the formulas
that we just derived for backpropagating
a matrix multiplication and I can backpropagate
through these expressions just fine.
And the reason this works is because
the dimensions have to work out.
So, let me give you an example.
Say I want to create dh.
Then what should dh be?
Number one, I have to know that
the shape of dh must be the same
as the shape of h.
And the shape of h is 32 by 64.
And then the other piece of information I know
is that dh
must be some kind of matrix multiplication
of dlogits with w2.
And dlogits
is 32 by 27
and w2 is
64 by 27. There is only
a single way to make the shape work out
in this case
and it is indeed the correct result.
In particular here, h
needs to be 32 by 64. The only
way to achieve that is to take dlogits
and matrix
multiply it with
you see how I have to take w2 but I have to
transpose it to make the dimensions work out.
So w2 transpose.
And it is the only way to make these
to matrix multiply those two pieces
to make the shapes work out. And that turns out
to be the correct formula. So if we come
here, we want
dh which is da and we see
that da is dl by
dd matrix multiply b transpose.
So that is dlogits multiply
and b is w2.
So w2 transpose which is exactly
what we have here. So
there is no need to remember these formulas.
Similarly, now if I
want dw2
well I know that it must be a matrix
multiplication of
dlogits and h
and maybe there is a few transpose
like there is one transpose in there as well.
And I don't know which way it is so I have to come to w2
and I see that its shape is
64 by 27
and that has to come from some matrix
multiplication of these two.
And so to get a 64 by 27
I need to take
h
I need to transpose it
and then I need to matrix multiply it
so that will become 64 by 32
and then I need to matrix multiply it with
32 by 27 and that's going to give me
a 64 by 27. So I need
to matrix multiply this with dlogits.shape
just like that. That's the only way
to make the dimensions work out and
just use matrix multiplication.
And if we come here, we see that
that's exactly what's here. So a transpose
a for us is h
multiplied with dlogits.
So that's w2
and then db2
is just
the
vertical sum and actually
in the same way, there's only one way to make
the shapes work out. I don't have to remember that
it's a vertical sum along the 0th axis
because that's the only way that this makes sense.
Because b2's shape is 27
so in order to get
a dlogits
here
it's 32 by 27 so
knowing that it's just sum over dlogits
in some direction
that direction must be 0
because I need to eliminate this dimension.
So it's this.
So this is
kind of like the hacky way.
Let me copy paste and delete that
and let me swing over here
and this is our backward pass for the linear layer.
Hopefully.
So now let's uncomment
these three and we're checking that
we got all the three
derivatives correct and
run
and we see that h,
w2 and b2 are all exactly correct.
So we backpropagate it through
a linear layer.
Now next up
we have derivative for the h
already and we need to backpropagate
through tanh into h preact.
So we want to derive
dh preact
and here we have to backpropagate through a tanh
and we've already done this in micrograd
and we remember that tanh is a very simple
backward formula. Now unfortunately
if I just put in d by dx of f
tanh of x into volt from alpha
it lets us down. It tells us that it's a
hyperbolic secant function squared
of x. It's not exactly helpful
but luckily google image
search does not let us down and it gives
us the simpler formula. In particular
if you have that a is equal to tanh
of z then da by
dz backpropagating through tanh
is just 1 minus a square
and take note that 1
minus a square a here is the
output of the tanh not the input to
the tanh z. So
the da by dz is here
formulated in terms of the output of that tanh
and here also
in google image search we have the full derivation
if you want to actually take the
actual definition of tanh and work
through the math to figure out 1 minus
tanh square of z. So
1 minus a square is
the local derivative. In our case
that is 1 minus
the output of tanh
square which here is h
so it's h square
and that is the local derivative
and then times the chain rule
dh. So
that is going to be our candidate implementation
so if we come here
and then uncomment
this let's hope for the best
and we have
the right answer. Okay next
up we have dh preact and
we want to backpropagate into the gain
the b in raw and the b in bias.
So here this is the bash norm
parameters b in gain and bias inside
the bash norm that take the b in raw
that is exact unit Gaussian
and they scale it and shift it
and these are the parameters of the
bash norm. Now here
we have a multiplication but
it's worth noting that this multiply is very very
different from this matrix multiply here
matrix multiply are dot products
between rows and columns of these
matrices involved. This is an
element wise multiply so things are quite a bit
simpler. Now we do have to
be careful with some of the broadcasting happening
in this line of code though. So you
see how b in gain and b in bias
are 1 by 64
but h preact and
b in raw are 32 by 64.
So
we have to be careful with that and make sure that all the shapes
work out fine and that the broadcasting is
correctly backpropagated. So
in particular let's start with db in gain
so db in gain
should be
and here this is again element wise
multiply and whenever we have a times
b equals c we saw that
the local derivative here is just if this
is a the local derivative is just the
b the other one. So this
local derivative is just b in raw
and then times chain rule
so dh preact.
So
this is the candidate
gradient. Now again
we have to be careful because b in gain
is of size 1 by 64
but this here
would be 32 by 64
and so
the correct thing to do
in this case of course is that b in gain
here is a rule vector of 64 numbers
it gets replicated vertically
in this operation
and so therefore the correct thing to do
is to sum because it's being replicated
and therefore
all the gradients in each of the rows
that are now flowing backwards
need to sum up to that same
tensor db in gain.
So we have to sum across all the zero
all the examples
basically which is the direction
in which this gets replicated
and now we have to be also careful because
b in gain is of shape
1 by 64. So in fact
I need to keep them as true
otherwise I would just get 64.
Now I don't actually
really remember why
the b in gain and the b in bias
I made them be 1 by 64
but the biases
b1 and b2
I just made them be one-dimensional vectors
they're not two-dimensional tensors
so I can't recall exactly why
I left the gain
and the bias as two-dimensional
but it doesn't really matter as long as you are consistent
and you're keeping it the same.
So in this case we want to keep the dimension
so that the tensor shapes work.
Next up we have
b in raw
so db in raw will be
b in gain
multiplying
dh preact
that's our chain rule.
Now what about the
dimensions of this?
We have to be careful, right?
So dh preact is
32 by 64
b in gain is 1 by 64
so it will just get replicated
to create this multiplication
which is the correct thing
because in a forward pass it also gets replicated
in just the same way.
So in fact we don't need the brackets here, we're done.
And the shapes are already correct.
And finally for the bias
very similar
this bias here is very very similar
to the bias we saw in the linear layer
and we see that the gradients
from h preact will simply flow
into the biases and add up
because these are just offsets.
And so basically we want this to be
dh preact but it needs
to sum along the right dimension
and in this case similar to the gain
we need to sum across the 0th
dimension, the examples
because of the way that the bias gets replicated
vertically and we also
want to have keep them as true.
And so this will basically take
this and sum it up and give us
a 1 by 64.
So this is the candidate implementation
it makes all the shapes work
let me bring it up
down here
and then let me uncomment these 3 lines
to check that
we are getting the correct result
for all the 3 tensors
and indeed we see that all of that
got backpropagated correctly.
So now we get to the batchnorm layer
we see how here bngain and bmbias
are the primers so the backpropagation ends
but bnraw now
is the output of the standardization
so here what I'm doing
of course is I'm breaking up the batchnorm
into manageable pieces so we can backpropagate
through each line individually
but basically what's happening is
bnmeani is the sum
so this is the
bnmeani
I apologize for the variable naming
bndiff is x minus mu
bndiff2
is x minus mu squared
here inside the variance
bnvar is the variance
so sigma square
this is bnvar
and it's basically the sum of squares
so this is the x minus mu
squared
and then the sum
now you'll notice one departure here
here it is normalized as 1 over m
which is the number of examples
here I'm normalizing
as 1 over n minus 1 instead of m
and this is deliberate and I'll come back to that
in a bit when we are at this line
it is something called the Bessel's correction
but this is how I want it
in our case
bnvar inv
then becomes basically bnvar
plus epsilon
epsilon is 1 negative 5
and then it's 1 over square root
is the same as raising to the power of
negative 0.5
because 0.5 is square root
and then negative makes it 1 over square root
so bnvar inv
is 1 over this denominator here
and then we can see that
bnraw which is the x hat here
is equal to the
bndiff the numerator
multiplied by the
bnvar inv
and this line here
that creates hpreact was the last piece
we've already backpropagated through it
so now what we want to do
is we are here
and we have bnraw
and we have to first backpropagate
into bndiff and bnvar inv
so now we are here
and we have dbnraw
and we need to backpropagate through this line
now I've written out the shapes here
and indeed
bnvar inv is a shape 1 by 64
so there is a
little bit of broadcasting happening here
that we have to be careful with
but it is just an elementwise simple multiplication
by now we should be pretty comfortable with that
to get dbndiff
we know that this is just
bnvar inv multiplied with
dbnraw
and conversely
to get dbnvar inv
we need to take
bndiff
and multiply that by dbnraw
so this is the candidate
but of course
we need to make sure that broadcasting is obeyed
so in particular
bnvar inv multiplying with dbnraw
will be okay
and give us 32 by 64 as we expect
but dbnvar inv
would be taking
a 32 by 64
multiplying it by
32 by 64
so this is a 32 by 64
but of course this bnvar inv
is only 1 by 64
so this second line here
needs a sum across the examples
and because there's this
dimension here we need to make sure that
keep them is true
so this is the candidate
let's erase this
and let's swing down here
and implement it
and then let's comment out
dbnvar inv
and dbndiff
now we'll actually notice
that dbndiff by the way
is going to be incorrect
so when I run this
bnvar inv is correct
bndiff is not correct
and this is actually expected
because we're not done
with bndiff
so in particular when we slide here
we see here that bnraw is a function of bndiff
but actually bnvar inv
is a function of bnvar
which is a function of bndiff too
which is a function of bndiff
so it comes here
so bdndiff
these variable names are crazy I'm sorry
it branches out into two branches
we've only done one branch of it
we have to continue our backpropagation
and eventually come back to bndiff
and then we'll be able to do a plus equals
and get the actual correct gradient
for now it is good to verify that cmp also works
it doesn't just lie to us
and tell us that everything is always correct
it can in fact detect when your
gradient is not correct
so that's good to see as well
okay so now we have the derivative here
and we're trying to backpropagate through this line
and because we're raising to a power of negative 0.5
I brought up the power rule
and we see that basically we have that
the bnvar will now be
we bring down the exponent
so negative 0.5 times x
which is this
and now raised to the power of
negative 0.5 minus 1
which is negative 1.5
now we would have to also apply
a small chain rule here in our head
because we need to take further
the derivative of bnvar
with respect to this expression here
inside the bracket
but because this is an element-wise operation
everything is fairly simple
that's just one
and so there's nothing to do there
so this is the local derivative
and then times the global derivative
to create the chain rule
this is just times the bnvar
so this is our candidate
let me bring this down
and uncomment the check
and we see that
we have the correct result
now before we backpropagate through the next line
I want to briefly talk about the node here
where I'm using the Bessel's correction
which is 1 over n minus 1
instead of dividing by n
when I normalize here
the sum of squares
now you'll notice that this is a departure from the paper
which uses 1 over n instead
not 1 over n minus 1
there m is rn
so it turns out that there are two ways
of estimating variance of an array
one is the biased estimate
which is 1 over n
and the other one is the unbiased estimate
which is 1 over n minus 1
now confusingly in the paper
it's not very clearly described
and also it's a detail that kind of matters
I think
we are using the biased version at training time
but later when they are talking about the inference
they are mentioning that
when they do the inference
they are using the unbiased estimate
which is the n minus 1 version
in basically
for inference
and to calibrate the running mean
and the running variance basically
and so they actually introduce
a train test mismatch
where in training they use the biased version
and in test time they use the unbiased version
I find this extremely confusing
you can read more about
the Bessel's correction
and why dividing by n minus 1
gives you a better estimate of the variance
in the case where you have population sizes
or samples from a population
that are very small
and that is indeed the case for us
because we are dealing with mini-matches
and these mini-matches are a small sample
of a larger population
which is the entire training set
and it turns out that
if you just estimate it using 1 over n
that actually almost always
underestimates the variance
and it is a biased estimator
and it is advised that you use the unbiased version
and divide by n minus 1
and you can go through this article here
that I liked that actually describes
the fall of reasoning
and I'll link it in the video description
now when you calculate the torshta variance
you'll notice that they take the unbiased flag
whether or not you want to divide by n
or n minus 1
so the default is for unbiased
but I believe unbiased by default
is true
I'm not sure why the docs here don't cite that
now in the batch norm
1 , the documentation again
is kind of wrong and confusing
it says that the standard deviation is calculated
via the biased estimator
but this is actually not exactly right
and people have pointed out that it is not right
in a number of issues since then
because actually the rabbit hole is deeper
and they follow the paper exactly
and they use the biased
version for training
but when they're estimating the running standard deviation
they are using the unbiased version
so again there's the train test mismatch
so long story short
I'm not a fan of train test discrepancies
I basically kind of consider
the fact that we use the biased version
the training time
and the unbiased test time
I basically consider this to be a bug
and I don't think that there's a good reason for that
it's not really
they don't really go into the detail
of the reasoning behind it in this paper
I basically prefer to use the Bessel's correction
in my own work
unfortunately BatchNorm does not take
a keyword argument that tells you whether or not
you want to use the unbiased version
or the biased version in both train and test
and so therefore anyone using BatchNormalization
basically in my view
has a bit of a bug in the code
and this turns out to be much less of a problem
if your batch
many batch sizes are a bit larger
but still I just find it kind of
unpalatable
so maybe someone can explain why this is okay
but for now I prefer to use the unbiased version
consistently both during training
and at test time
and that's why I'm using 1 over n minus 1 here
okay so let's now actually backpropagate
through this line
so
the first thing that I always like to do
is I like to scrutinize the shapes first
so in particular here looking at the shapes
of what's involved
I see that bnvar shape is 1 by 64
so it's a row vector
and bndiff2.shape is 32 by 64
so I can see that
so clearly here we're doing a sum
over the 0th axis
to squash the first dimension
of the shapes here
using a sum
so that right away actually hints to me
that there will be some kind of a replication
or broadcasting in the backward pass
and maybe you're noticing the pattern here
but basically any time you have a sum
in the forward pass
that turns into a replication
or broadcasting in the backward pass
along the same dimension
and conversely when we have a replication
or a broadcasting in the forward pass
that indicates a variable reuse
and so in the backward pass
that turns into a sum
over the exact same dimension
and so hopefully you're noticing that duality
that those two are kind of like the opposites
of each other in the forward and backward pass
now once we understand the shapes
the next thing I like to do always
is I like to look at a toy example in my head
to sort of just like understand roughly how
the variable dependencies go
in the mathematical formula
so here we have
a two-dimensional array
b and div 2 which we are scaling
by a constant and then we are summing
vertically over the columns
so if we have a 2x2 matrix a
and then we sum over the columns
and scale we would get a
row vector b1 b2 and
b1 depends on a in this way
where it's just sum that is scaled
of a and b2
in this way where it's the second column
summed and scaled
and so looking at this basically
what we want to do is
we have the derivatives on b1 and b2
and we want to back propagate them into a's
and so it's clear that just
differentiating in your head
the local derivative here is 1 over n-1
times 1
for each one of these a's
and
basically the derivative of b1
has to flow through the columns of a
scaled by 1 over n-1
and that's roughly
what's happening here
so intuitively the derivative flow
tells us that
db and df2
will be
the local derivative of this operation
and there are many ways to do this by the way
but I like to do something like this
torch dot ones like
of b and df2
so I'll create a large array
two dimensional of ones
and then I will scale it
so 1.0 divided by n-1
so this is an array of
1 over n-1
and that's sort of like the local derivative
and now for the chain rule
I will simply just multiply it by
db and var
and notice here what's going to happen
this is 32 by 64
and this is just 1 by 64
so I'm letting the broadcasting
do the replication
because internally in pytorch
basically db and var
which is 1 by 64 row vector
will in this multiplication get
copied vertically
until the two are of the same shape
and then there will be an elementwise multiply
so the broadcasting is basically doing the replication
and I will end up
with the derivatives of db and df2
here
so this is the candidate solution
let's bring it down here
let's uncomment this line
where we check it
and let's hope for the best
and indeed we see that this is the correct formula
next up let's differentiate here
into b and df
so here we have that b and df
is elementwise squared to create b and df2
so this is a
relatively simple derivative
because it's a simple elementwise operation
so it's kind of like the scalar case
and we have that db and df
should be
if this is x squared
then the derivative of this is 2x
so it's simply 2 times b and df
that's the local derivative
and then times chain rule
and the shape of these is the same
they are of the same shape
so times this
so that's the backward pass for this variable
let me bring it down here
I've already calculated db and df
so this is just the end of the other
branch coming back to b and df
because b and df
were already back propagated to
way over here
from b and raw
so we now completed the second branch
and so that's why I have to do plus equals
and if you recall
we had an incorrect derivative for b and df before
and I'm hoping that once we append
this last missing piece
we have the exact correctness
so let's run
and b and df now actually shows
the exact correct derivative
so that's comforting
okay so let's now back propagate
through this line here
the first thing we do of course
is we check the shapes
and I wrote them out here
and basically the shape of this
is 32 by 64
h pre bn is the same shape
but b and mean i is a row vector
1 by 64
so this minus here will actually do broadcasting
and so we have to be careful with that
again because of the duality
a broadcasting in the forward pass
means a variable reuse
and therefore there will be a sum
in the backward pass
so let's write out the backward pass here now
back propagate into the h pre bn
because these are the same shape
then the local derivative
for each one of the elements here
is just 1 for the corresponding element
in here
so basically what this means is that
the gradient just simply copies
it's just a variable assignment
so I'm just going to clone this tensor
just for safety to create an exact copy
of db and diff
and then here
to back propagate into this one
what I'm inclined to do here
is
d bn mean i
will basically be
what is the local derivative
well it's negative torch.once like
of the shape of
b and diff
right
so
and then times
the
derivative here
db and diff
and this here
is the back propagation
for the replicated
b and mean i
so I still have to back propagate
through the replication
in the broadcasting
and I do that by doing a sum
so I'm going to take this whole thing
and I'm going to do a sum
and I'm going to do a replication
so if you scrutinize this by the way
you'll notice that
this is the same shape as that
and so what I'm doing
what I'm doing here doesn't actually make that much sense
because it's just a
array of ones multiplying db and diff
so in fact I can just do
this
and that is equivalent
so this is the candidate
backward pass
let me copy it here
let me comment out this one
and this one
enter
and it's wrong
damn
actually sorry
this is supposed to be wrong
and it's supposed to be wrong because
we are back propagating
from b and diff into h pre bn
but we're not done
because b and mean i depends
on h pre bn and there will be
a second portion of that derivative coming from
this second branch
but we're not done yet and we expect it to be incorrect
so there you go
so let's now back propagate from b and mean i
into h pre bn
and so here again we have to be careful
because there's a broadcasting along
or there's a sum along the 0th dimension
so this will turn into broadcasting
in the backward pass now
and I'm going to go a little bit faster on this line
because it is very similar to the line
that we had before
multiple lines in the past in fact
so d h pre bn
will be
the gradient will be scaled
by 1 over n and then
basically this gradient here on d bn
mean i
is going to be scaled by 1 over n
and then it's going to flow across
all the columns and deposit itself
into d h pre bn
so what we want is this thing
scaled by 1 over n
let me put the constant up front here
so scale down the gradient
and we need to replicate it
across all the
across all the rows here
so I like to do that
by torch dot once like
of basically
h pre bn
and I will let broadcasting
do the work of
replication
so
A
like that
so this is
d h pre bn
and hopefully
we can plus equals that
so this here is broadcasting
and then this is the scaling
so this should be correct
okay
so that completes the backpropagation
let's backpropagate through the linear layer 1
here now because
everything is getting a little vertically crazy
I copy pasted the line here
and let's just backpropagate through this one line
so first of course
we inspect the shapes and we see that
this is 32 by 64
mcat is 32
by 30
w1 is 30 by 64
and b1 is just 64
so as I mentioned
backpropagating through linear layers
is fairly easy just by matching the shapes
so let's do that
we have that d mcat
should be
some matrix multiplication
of d h pre bn with
w1 and 1 transpose
thrown in there
so to make mcat
be 32 by 30
I need to take
d h pre bn
32 by 64
and multiply it by
w1 dot transpose
...
to get d w1
I need to end up with
30 by 64
so to get that I need to take
mcat transpose
...
and multiply that by
d h pre bn
...
and finally to get
d b1
this is an addition
and we saw that basically
I need to just sum the elements
in d h pre bn along some dimensions
and to make the dimensions work out
I need to sum along the 0th axis
here to eliminate
this dimension
and we do not keep dims
so that we want to just get a single
one-dimensional vector of 64
so these are the claimed derivatives
let me put that here
and let me
uncomment three lines
and cross our fingers
everything is great
okay so we now continue almost there
we have the derivative of mcat
and we want to backpropagate
into mb
so I again copied this line over here
so this is the forward pass
and then this is the shapes
so remember that the shape here
was 32 by 30
and the original shape of mb
was 32 by 3 by 10
so this layer in the forward pass
as you recall did the concatenation
of these three 10-dimensional
character vectors
and so now we just want to undo that
so this is actually a relatively
simple iteration because
the backward pass of the
what is the view? view is just a
representation of the array
it's just a logical form of how
you interpret the array
so let's just reinterpret it
to be what it was before
so in other words dmb is not 32 by 30
it is basically dmpcat
but if you view it
as the original shape
so just m.shape
you can pass and tuple
into view
and so this should just be
okay
we just re-represent that view
and then we uncomment this line here
and hopefully
yeah, so the derivative of m
is correct
so in this case we just have to re-represent
the shape of those derivatives
into the original view
so now we are at the final line
and the only thing that's left to backpropagate through
is this indexing operation here
m is c at xb
or I copy pasted this line here
and let's look at the shapes of everything that's involved
and remind ourselves how this worked
so m.shape
was 32 by 3 by 10
so it's 32 examples
and then we have 3 characters
each one of them has a 10 dimensional
embedding
and this was achieved by taking the
lookup table c which have 27
possible characters
each of them 10 dimensional
and we looked up at the rows
that were specified
inside this tensor xb
so xb is 32 by 3
and it's basically giving us for each example
the identity or the index
of which character
is part of that example
and so here I'm showing the first 5 rows
of this tensor xb
and so we can see that for example here
it was the first example in this batch
is that the first character
and the first character and the fourth character
comes into the neural net
and then we want to predict the next character
in the sequence after the character is 114
so basically
what's happening here is
there are integers inside xb
and each one of these integers
is specifying which row of c
we want to pluck out
right and then we arrange
those rows that we've plucked out
into 32 by 3 by 10 tensor
and we just package them in
we just package them into this tensor
and now what's happening
is that we have dimp
so for every one of these
basically plucked out rows
we have their gradients now
but they're arranged inside this 32 by 3 by 10 tensor
so all we have to do now
is we just need to route this gradient
backwards through this assignment
so we need to find which row of c
that every one of these
10 dimensional embeddings come from
and then we need to deposit them
into dc
so we just need to undo the indexing
and of course
if any of these rows of c
were used multiple times
which almost certainly is the case
like the row 1 and 1 was used multiple times
then we have to remember that the gradients
that arrive there have to add
so for each occurrence
we have to have an addition
so let's now write this out
and I don't actually know of like
a much better way to do this
than a for loop unfortunately in python
so maybe someone can come up with
a vectorized efficient operation
but for now let's just use for loops
so let me create torch.zeros like c
and I'm going to utilize just
a 27 by 10 tensor of all zeros
and then honestly
for k in range xb.shape at 0
maybe someone has a better way to do this
but for j in range xb.shape at 1
this is going to iterate over
all the elements of xb
all these integers
and then let's get the index
at this position
so the index is basically
the value of xb
and then let's get the index
at this position
which is basically xb at kj
so an example of that
is 11 or 14 and so on
and now in a forward pass
we took
we basically took
um
the row of c at index
and we deposited it
into emb at k at j
that's what happened
that's where they are packaged
so now we need to go backwards
and we just need to route
deemb at the position
kj
we now have these derivatives
for each position
and it's 10 dimensional
and you just need to go into the correct
row of c
so dc rather
at ix is this
but plus equals
because there could be multiple occurrences
like the same row could have been used
many many times
and so all those derivatives will
just go backwards through the indexing
and they will add
so this is my candidate
solution
let's copy it here
let's uncomment this
and cross our fingers
yay
so that's it
we've backpropagated through
this entire beast
so there we go
totally makes sense
so now we come to exercise 2
it basically turns out that in this first exercise
we were doing way too much work
we were backpropagating way too much
and it was all good practice and so on
but it's not what you would do in practice
and the reason for that is for example
here I separated out this loss calculation
over multiple lines
and I broke it up all to like
its smallest atomic pieces
and we backpropagated through all of those individually
but it turns out that if you just look at
the mathematical expression for the loss
then actually you can do
the differentiation on pen and paper
and a lot of terms cancel and simplify
and the mathematical expression you end up with
is significantly shorter
and easier to implement
than backpropagating through all the little pieces
of everything you've done
so before we had this complicated forward pass
going from logits to the loss
but in pytorch everything can just be
glued together into a single call
at that cross entropy
you just pass in logits and the labels
and you get the exact same loss
as I verify here
so our previous loss and the fast loss
coming from the chunk of operations
as a single mathematical expression
is much faster than the backward pass
it's also much much faster in backward pass
and the reason for that is if you just look at
the mathematical form of this and differentiate again
you will end up with a very small and short expression
so that's what we want to do here
we want to in a single operation
or in a single go or like very quickly
go directly into dlogits
and we need to implement dlogits
as a function of logits
and yb's
but it will be significantly shorter
than whatever we did here
where to get to dlogits
we need to go all the way here
so all of this work can be skipped
in a much much simpler mathematical expression
that you can implement here
so you can
give it a shot yourself
basically look at what exactly
is the mathematical expression of loss
and differentiate with respect to the logits
so let me show you
a hint
you can of course try it fully yourself
but if not I can give you some hint
of how to get started mathematically
so basically what's happening here
is we have logits
then there's the softmax
that takes the logits and gives you probabilities
then we are using the identity
of the correct next character
to pluck out a row of probabilities
take the negative log of it
to get our negative log probability
and then we average up
all the log probabilities
or negative log probabilities
to get our loss
so basically what we have
is for a single individual example
we have that loss is equal to
where p here is kind of like
thought of as a vector
of all the probabilities
so at the yth position
where y is the label
and we have that p here of course
is the softmax
so the ith component of p
of this probability vector
is just the softmax function
so raising all the logits
basically to the power of e
and normalizing
so everything sums to one
now if you write out
this expression here
you can just write out the softmax
and then basically what we're interested in
is we're interested in the derivative of the loss
with respect to the ith logit
and so basically it's a d by dLi
of this expression here
where we have l indexed
with the specific label y
and on the bottom we have a sum over j
of e to the lj
and the negative log of all that
so potentially give it a shot
pen and paper and see if you can actually
derive the expression for the loss by dLi
and to implement it here
okay so I'm going to give away the result here
so this is some of the math I did
to derive the gradients
analytically
and so we see here that I'm just applying
the rules of calculus from your first or second year
of bachelor's degree if you took it
and we see that the expressions
actually simplify quite a bit
you have to separate out the analysis
in the case where the ith index
that you're interested in inside logits
is either equal to the label
or it's not equal to the label
in a slightly different way
and what we end up with is something
very very simple
we either end up with basically p at i
where p is again this vector of
probabilities after a softmax
or p at i minus one
where we just simply subtract a one
but in any case we just need to calculate
the softmax p
and then in the correct dimension
we need to subtract a one
and that's the gradient
the form that it takes analytically
so let's implement this basically
but here we are working with batches of examples
so we have to be careful of that
and then the loss for a batch
is the average loss over all the examples
so in other words
is the example for all the individual examples
is the loss for each individual example
summed up and then divided by n
and we have to backpropagate through that
as well and be careful with it
so dlogits
is going to be f dot softmax
pytorch has a softmax function
that you can call
and we want to apply the softmax
on the logits and we want to go
in the dimension
that is one
so basically we want to do the softmax
along the rows of these logits
then at the correct positions
we need to subtract a one
so dlogits at iterating over all the rows
and indexing
into the columns
provided by the correct labels
inside yb
we need to subtract one
and then finally it's the average loss
that is the loss
so in average there's a one over n
of all the losses added up
and so we need to also backpropagate
through that division
so the gradient has to be scaled down
by n as well
because of the mean
but this otherwise should be the result
so now if we verify this
we see that we don't get an exact match
but at the same time
the maximum difference from
logits from pytorch
and rdlogits here
is on the order of 5e-9
so it's a tiny tiny number
so because of floating point wonkiness
we don't get the exact bitwise result
but we basically get
the correct answer
approximately
now I'd like to pause here briefly
before we move on to the next exercise
because I'd like us to get an intuitive sense
of what dlogits is
because it has a beautiful and very simple
explanation honestly
so here I'm taking dlogits
and I'm visualizing it
and I see that we have a batch of 32 examples
of 27 characters
and what is dlogits intuitively?
dlogits is the probabilities
that the probabilities matrix
in the forward pass
but then here these black squares
are the positions of the correct indices
where we subtracted a 1
and so what is this doing?
these are the derivatives on dlogits
and so let's look at
just the first row here
so that's what I'm doing here
I'm calculating the probabilities
and then I'm taking just the first row
and this is the probability row
and then dlogits of the first row
and multiplying by n
just for us so that
we don't have the scaling by n in here
and everything is more interpretable
we see that it's exactly equal to the probability
of course but then the position
of the correct index has a minus equals 1
so minus 1 on that position
and so notice that
if you take dlogits at 0
and you sum it
it actually sums to 0
and so you should think of these
gradients here
at each cell
as like a force
we are going to be basically
pulling down on the probabilities
of the incorrect characters
and we're going to be pulling up
on the probability
at the correct index
and that's what's basically happening
in each row
and the amount of push and pull
is exactly equalized
because the sum is 0
and the amount to which we pull down
on the probabilities
and the amount that we push up
on the probability of the correct character
is equal
so the repulsion and the attraction are equal
and think of the neural net now
as a massive pulley system
or something like that
we're up here on top of dlogits
and we're pulling up
we're pulling down the probabilities of incorrect
and pulling up the probability of the correct
and in this complicated pulley system
we think of it as sort of like
this tension translating to this
complicating pulley mechanism
and then eventually we get a tug
on the weights and the biases
and basically in each update
we just kind of like tug in the direction
that we'd like for each of these elements
and the parameters are slowly given in
to the tug and that's what training in neural net
kind of like looks like on a high level
and so I think the forces of push and pull
in these gradients are actually
very intuitive here
we're pushing and pulling on the correct answer
and the amount of force that we're applying
is actually proportional to
the probabilities that came out
in the forward pass
and so for example if our probabilities came out
exactly correct so they would have had
zero everywhere except for one
at the correct position
then the dlogits would be all
a row of zeros for that example
there would be no push and pull
so the amount to which your prediction is incorrect
is exactly the amount
by which you're going to get a pull
or a push in that dimension
so if you have for example
a very confidently mispredicted element here
then what's going to happen is
that element is going to be pulled down
very heavily and the correct answer
is going to be pulled up to the same amount
and the other characters
are not going to be influenced too much
so the amount to which
you mispredict is then proportional
to the strength of the pull
and that's happening independently
in all the dimensions of this tensor
and it's sort of very intuitive
and very easy to think through
and that's basically the magic of the cross entropy loss
and what it's doing dynamically
in the backward pass of the neural net
so now we get to exercise number three
which is a very fun exercise
depending on your definition of fun
and we are going to do for batch normalization
exactly what we did for cross entropy loss
in exercise number two
that is we are going to consider it as a glued
single mathematical expression
and back propagate through it in a very efficient manner
because we are going to derive a much simpler formula
for the backward pass of batch normalization
and we're going to do that
using pen and paper
so previously we've broken up batch normalization
into all of the little intermediate pieces
and all the atomic operations inside it
and then we back propagated through it
one by one
now we just have a single sort of forward pass
of a batch form
and it's all glued together
and we see that we get the exact same result as before
now for the backward pass
we'd like to also implement
a single formula basically
for back propagating through this entire operation
that is the batch normalization
so in the forward pass previously
we took h pre bn
the hidden states of the pre batch normalization
and created h preact
which is the hidden states
just before the activation
in the batch normalization paper
h pre bn is x
and h preact is y
so in the backward pass what we'd like to do now
is we have dh preact
and we'd like to produce dh pre bn
and we'd like to do that in a very efficient manner
so that's the name of the game
calculate dh pre bn
given dh preact
and for the purposes of this exercise
we're going to ignore gamma and beta
and their derivatives
because they take on a very simple form
in a very similar way to what we did up above
so let's calculate this
given that right here
so to help you a little bit
like I did before
I started off the implementation here
on pen and paper
and I took two sheets of paper
to derive the mathematical formulas
for the backward pass
so to solve the problem
just write out the mu sigma square variance
xi hat and yi
exactly as in the paper
except for the Bessel correction
and then in the backward pass
we have the derivative of the laws
with respect to all the elements of y
and remember that y is a vector
there's multiple numbers here
so we have all the derivatives
with respect to all the y's
and then there's a gamma and a beta
and this is kind of like the compute graph
the gamma and the beta
there's the x hat
and then the mu and the sigma square
and the x
so we have dl by dyi
and we want dl by dxi
for all the i's in these vectors
so
this is the compute graph
and you have to be careful because
I'm trying to note here that
these are vectors
there's many nodes here inside x
x hat and y
but mu and sigma
sorry sigma square
so you have to be careful with that
you have to imagine there's multiple nodes here
or you're going to get your math wrong
so as an example
I would suggest that you go in the following order
one, two, three, four
in terms of the back propagation
so back propagate into x hat
then into sigma square
then into mu and then into x
just like in a topological sort
in micrograd we would go from right to left
you're doing the exact same thing
except you're doing it with symbols
and on a piece of paper
so for number one
I'm not giving away too much
if you want dl of
dxi hat
then we just take dl by dyi
and multiply it by gamma
because of this expression here
where any individual yi is just gamma
times xi hat plus beta
so it didn't help you
too much there
but this gives you basically the derivatives
for all the x hats
and so now try to go through this computational graph
and derive
what is dl by d sigma square
and then what is dl by d mu
and then what is dl by dx
eventually
so give it a go
and I'm going to be revealing the answer
one piece at a time
okay, so to get dl by d sigma square
we have to remember again, like I mentioned
that there are many x hats here
and remember that sigma square
is just a single individual number here
so when we look at the expression
for dl by d sigma square
we have that we have to actually
consider all the possible paths
that
we basically have that
there's many x hats
and they all feed off from
they all depend on sigma square
so sigma square has a large fan out
there's lots of arrows coming out from sigma square
into all the x hats
and then there's a back-replicating signal
from each x hat into sigma square
and that's why we actually need to sum over
all those i's
into 1 to m
of the dl by dx hat
which is the global gradient
times
the xi hat by d sigma square
which is the local gradient
of this operation here
and then mathematically
I'm just working it out here
and I'm simplifying and you get a certain expression
for dl by d sigma square
and we're going to be using this expression
when we back-propagate into mu
and then eventually into x
so now let's continue our back-propagation into mu
which is dl by d mu
now again be careful
that mu influences x hat
and x hat is actually lots of values
so for example if our mini-batch size is 32
as it is in our example that we were working on
then this is 32 numbers
and 32 arrows going back to mu
and then mu going to sigma square
is just a single arrow
because sigma square is a scalar
so in total there are 33 arrows
emanating from mu
and then all of them have gradients coming into mu
and they all need to be summed up
and so that's why
when we look at the expression for dl by d mu
I'm summing up over all the gradients
of dl by dx i hat
times dx i hat by d mu
so that's this arrow
and that's 32 arrows here
and then plus the one arrow from here
which is dl by d sigma square
times d sigma square by d mu
so now we have to work out
that expression
and let me just reveal the rest of it
simplifying here is not complicated
the first term
and you just get an expression here
for the second term though
there's something really interesting that happens
when we look at d sigma square by d mu
and we simplify
at one point if we assume
that in a special case where mu is actually
the average of xi's
as it is in this case
then if we plug that in
then actually the gradient vanishes
and becomes exactly zero
and that makes the entire second term cancel
and so
these
if you have a mathematical expression like this
and you look at d sigma square by d mu
you would get some mathematical formula
for how mu impacts sigma square
but if it is the special case
that mu is actually equal to the average
as it is in the case of batch normalization
that gradient will actually vanish
and become zero
so the whole term cancels
and we just get a fairly straightforward expression here
for dl by d mu
okay and now we get to the craziest part
which is deriving dl by d xi
which is ultimately what we're after
now let's count
first of all how many numbers are there inside x
as I mentioned there are 32 numbers
there are 32 little xi's
and let's count the number of arrows
emanating from each xi
there's an arrow going to mu
an arrow going to sigma square
and then there's an arrow going to x hat
but this arrow here
let's scrutinize that a little bit
each xi hat is just a function of xi
and all the other scalars
so xi hat
only depends on xi
and all the other x's
and so therefore
there are actually in this single arrow
there are 32 arrows
but those 32 arrows are going exactly parallel
they don't interfere
they're just going parallel between x and x hat
you can look at it that way
and so how many arrows are emanating from each xi
there are three arrows
mu sigma square
and the associated x hat
and so in back propagation
we now need to apply the chain rule
and we need to add up those three contributions
like if I just write that out
we have
we're going through
we're chaining through mu sigma square
and through x hat
and those three terms are just here
now we already have three of these
we have dl by d xi hat
we have dl by d mu
which we derived here
and we have dl by d sigma square
but we need three other terms here
this one, this one, and this one
so I invite you to try to derive them
if you find it complicated
you're just looking at these expressions here
and differentiating with respect to xi
so give it a shot
but here's the result
or at least what I got
I'm just differentiating with respect to xi
for all of these expressions
and honestly I don't think there's anything too tricky here
it's basic calculus
now what gets a little bit more tricky
is we are now going to plug everything together
so all of these terms
multiplied with all of these terms
and added up according to this formula
and that gets a little bit hairy
so what ends up happening is
you get a large expression
and the thing to be very careful with here
of course is
we are working with a dl by d xi
for a specific i here
but when we are plugging in some of these terms
like say
this term here
dl by d sigma squared
you see how dl by d sigma squared
I end up with an expression
and I'm iterating over little i's here
but I can't use i as the variable
when I plug in here
because this is a different i from this i
this i here is just a placeholder
like a local variable for a for loop
in here
so here when I plug that in
you notice that I rename the i to a j
because I need to make sure that this j
is not this i
this j is like a little local iterator
over 32 terms
and so you have to be careful with that
when you are plugging in the expressions from here to here
you may have to rename i's into j's
but you have to be very careful
what is actually an i
with respect to dl by d xi
so some of these are j's
some of these are i's
and then we simplify this expression
and I guess like
the big thing to notice here is
a bunch of terms are just going to come out to the front
and you can refactor them
there is a sigma squared plus epsilon
raised to the power of negative 3 over 2
this sigma squared plus epsilon
can be actually separated out into 3 terms
each of them are sigma squared plus epsilon
raised to the power of negative 1 over 2
so the 3 of them multiplied
is equal to this
and then those 3 terms can go different places
because of the multiplication
so one of them actually comes out to the front
and will end up here outside
one of them joins up with this term
and one of them joins up with this other term
and then when you simplify the expression
you will notice that
some of these terms that are coming out
are just the xi hats
so you can simplify just by rewriting that
and what we end up with at the end
is a fairly simple mathematical expression
over here that I cannot simplify further
but basically you'll notice that
it only uses the stuff we have
and it derives the thing we need
so we have dl by dy
for all the i's
and those are used plenty of times here
and also in addition what we're using
is these xi hats and xj hats
and they just come from the forward pass
and otherwise this is a
simple expression and it gives us
dl by d xi for all the i's
and that's ultimately what we're interested in
so that's the end of
batch norm
backward pass analytically
let's now implement this final result
okay so I implemented the expression
into a single line of code here
and you can see that the max diff
is tiny so this is the correct implementation
of this formula
now I'll just
basically tell you that getting this
formula here from this mathematical expression
was not trivial and there's a lot
going on packed into this one formula
and this is a whole exercise by itself
because you have to consider
the fact that this formula here
is just for a single neuron
and a batch of 32 examples
but what I'm doing here is I'm actually
we actually have 64 neurons
and so this expression has to in parallel
evaluate the batch norm backward pass
for all of those 64 neurons
in parallel and independently
so this has to happen basically in every single
column of
the inputs here
and in addition to that
you see how there are a bunch of sums here
and I want to make sure that when I do those sums
that they broadcast correctly onto everything else
that's here and so getting this expression
is just like highly non-trivial
and I invite you to basically look through it
and step through it and it's a whole exercise
to make sure that this checks out
but once all the shapes agree
and once you convince yourself that it's correct
you can also verify that PyTorch
gets the exact same answer as well
and so that gives you a lot of peace of mind
that this mathematical formula is correctly
implemented here and broadcasted correctly
and replicated in parallel
for all of the 64 neurons
inside this batch norm layer
okay and finally exercise number 4
asks you to put it all together
and here we have a redefinition
of the entire problem
so you see that we re-initialized the neural net from scratch
and everything and then here
instead of calling loss that backward
we want to have the manual back propagation
here as we derived it up above
so go up copy paste
all the chunks of code that we've already derived
put them here and derive your own gradients
and then optimize this model
using this neural net
basically using your own gradients
all the way to the calibration of the batch norm
and the evaluation of the loss
and I was able to achieve quite a good loss
basically the same loss you would achieve before
and that shouldn't be surprising
because all we've done is we've
really got into loss that backward
and we've pulled out all the code
and inserted it here
but those gradients are identical
and everything is identical
and the results are identical
it's just that we have full visibility
in this specific case
okay and this is all of our code
this is the full backward pass
using basically the simplified backward pass
for the cross entropy loss
and the batch normalization
so back propagating through cross entropy
the second layer
the 10H null linearity
the batch normalization
through the first layer
and through the embedding
and so you see that this is only maybe
what is this 20 lines of code or something like that
and that's what gives us gradients
in this case loss that backward
so the way I have the code set up is
you should be able to run this entire cell
once you fill this in
and this will run for only 100 iterations
and then break
and it breaks because it gives you an opportunity
to check your gradients against PyTorch
so here our gradients we see
are not exactly equal
they are approximately equal
and the differences are tiny
one in negative nine or so
and I don't exactly know where they're coming from
to be honest
but if I'm basically correct
we can take out the gradient checking
we can disable this breaking statement
and then we can
basically disable loss that backward
we don't need it anymore
feels amazing to say that
and then here
when we are doing the update
we're not going to use p.grad
this is the old way of PyTorch
we don't have that anymore
because we're not doing backward
we are going to use this update
I'm grading over
I've arranged the grads to be in the same order
as the parameters
and I'm zipping them up
the gradients and the parameters
into p and grad
and then here I'm going to step with
just the grad that we derived manually
so the last piece
is that none of this now requires
gradients from PyTorch
and so one thing you can do here
is you can do
with torch.nograd
and offset this whole code block
and really what you're saying is
you're telling PyTorch that hey
I'm not going to call backward on any of this
and this allows PyTorch to be
a bit more efficient with all of it
and then we should be able to just run this
and
it's running
and you see that
loss that backward is commented out
and we're optimizing
so we're going to leave this run
and hopefully
we get a good result
okay so I allowed the neural net
optimization then here
I calibrate the BatchNorm parameters
because I did not keep track of the running
mean and variance
in the training loop
then here I ran the loss
and you see that we actually obtained a pretty good loss
very similar to what we've achieved before
and then here I'm sampling from the model
and we see some of the name-like gibberish
that we're sort of used to
so basically the model worked and samples
pretty decent results
compared to what we were used to
so everything is the same but of course
the big deal is that we did not use lots of backward
we did not use PyTorch AutoGrad
and we estimated our gradients ourselves
by hand
and so hopefully you're looking at this
the backward pass of this neural net
and you're thinking to yourself
actually that's not too complicated
each one of these layers is like three lines of code
or something like that
and most of it is fairly straightforward
potentially with the notable exception
of the BatchNormalization backward pass
otherwise it's pretty good
okay and that's everything I wanted to cover
so hopefully you found this interesting
and what I liked about it honestly is that
it gave us a very nice diversity of layers
to backpropagate through
and I think it gives a pretty nice
and comprehensive sense of how these
backward passes are implemented
and how they work
and you'd be able to derive them yourself
but of course in practice you probably don't want to
and you want to use the PyTorch AutoGrad
but hopefully you have some intuition about
how gradients flow backwards through the neural net
starting at the loss
and how they flow through all the variables
and if you understood a good chunk of it
and if you have a sense of that
then you can count yourself as one of these
buff dojis on the left
instead of the dojis on the right here
now in the next lecture
we're actually going to go to recurrent neural nets
LSTMs and all the other variants
of RNNs
and we're going to start to complexify the architecture
and start to achieve better log likelihoods
and so I'm really looking forward to that
and I'll see you then