Hi everyone. Today we are continuing our implementation of MakeMore.
Now in the last lecture we implemented the bigram language model and we implemented it both using
counts and also using a super simple neural network that had a single linear layer. Now
this is the Jupyter notebook that we built out last lecture and we saw that the way we approached
this is that we looked at only the single previous character and we predicted the distribution for
the character that would go next in the sequence and we did that by taking counts and normalizing
them into probabilities so that each row here sums to one. Now this is all well and good if
you only have one character of previous context and this works and it's approachable. The problem
with this model of course is that the predictions from this model are not very good because you only
take one character of context so the model didn't produce very name-like sounding things.
Now
the problem with this approach though is that if we are to take more context into account
when predicting the next character in a sequence things quickly blow up and this table the size
of this table grows and in fact it grows exponentially with the length of the context
because if we only take a single character at a time that's 27 possibilities of context
but if we take two characters in the past and try to predict the third one suddenly the number
of rows in this matrix you can look at it that way is 27 times 27 so there's 720
possibilities for what could have come in the context. If we take three characters as the
context suddenly we have 20 000 possibilities of context and so that's just way too many rows
of this matrix it's way too few counts for each possibility and the whole thing just kind of
explodes and doesn't work very well. So that's why today we're going to move on to this bullet
point here and we're going to implement a multi-layer perceptron model to predict the next
character in a sequence and this modeling approach that we're going to adopt follows this
paper Benjou et al. 2003. So I have the paper pulled up here now this isn't the very first
paper that proposed the use of multi-layer perceptrons or neural networks to predict the
next character or token in a sequence but it's definitely one that is was very influential
around that time it is very often cited to stand in for this idea and I think it's a very nice
write-up and so this is the paper that we're going to first look at and then implement.
Now this paper has 19 pages so we don't have time to go into the full detail of this paper but I
invite you to read it it's very readable interesting and has a lot of interesting
ideas in it as well in the introduction they describe the exact same problem I just described
and then to address it they propose the following model now keep in mind that we are building a
character level language model so we're working on the level of characters in this paper they
have a vocabulary of seventeen thousand possible words and they instead build a word level and
language model but we're going to still stick with the characters but we'll take the same modeling
approach now what they do is basically they propose to take every one of these words seventeen
thousand words and they're going to associate to each word a say thirty dimensional feature vector
so every word is now embedded into a thirty dimensional space you can think of it that way
so we have seventeen thousand points or vectors in a thirty dimensional space and that's you might
imagine that's very crowded that's a lot of points for a very small space now in the beginning these
words are initialized completely randomly so they're spread out at random but then we're
going to tune these embeddings of these words using that propagation so during the course of
training of this neural network these points or vectors are going to basically move around in this
space and you might imagine that for example words that have very similar meanings or there are
indeed synonyms of each other might end up in a very similar part of the space and conversely words
in very different things would go somewhere else in the space now their modeling approach otherwise
is identical to ours they are using a multi-layer neural network to predict the next word given the
previous words and to train the neural network they are maximizing the log likelihood of the
training data just like we did so the modeling approach itself is identical now here they have
a concrete example of this intuition why does it work basically suppose that for example you are
trying to predict a dog was running in a blank
now suppose that the exact phrase a dog was running in a has never occurred in the training
data and here you are at sort of test time later when the model is deployed somewhere
and it's trying to make a sentence and it's saying a dog was running in a blank and because
it's never encountered this exact phrase in the training set you're out of distribution as we say
like you don't have fundamentally any reason to suspect um what might come next but this approach
allows you to get around that because maybe you didn't see the exact phrase a dog was running in a
something but maybe you've seen similar phrases maybe you've seen the phrase the dog was running
in a blank and maybe your network has learned that a and the are like frequently are interchangeable
with each other and so maybe it took the embedding for a and the embedding for the
and it actually put them like nearby each other in the space and so you can transfer knowledge
through that embedding and you can generalize in that way similarly the network could know that cats
and dogs are animals and they co-occur in lots of very similar contexts and so even though you
haven't seen this exact phrase or if you haven't seen exactly walking or running you can through
the embedding space transfer knowledge and you can generalize to novel scenarios so let's now scroll
down to the diagram of the neural network they have a nice diagram here and in this example
we are taking three previous words and we are trying to predict the fourth word in a sequence
now these three previous words as i mentioned we have a vocabulary of 17 000
possible words so every one of these basically are the index of the incoming word
and because there are 17 000 words this is an integer between 0 and 16 999
now there's also a lookup table that they call c this lookup table is a matrix that is 17 000 by
and basically what we're doing here is we're treating this as a lookup table
and so every index is plucking out a row of this embedding matrix so that each index is converted
to the 30-dimensional vector that corresponds to the embedding vector for that word
so here we have the input layer of 30 neurons for three words making up 90 neurons in total
and here they're saying that this matrix c is shared across all the words so we're always in a
indexing into the same matrix C over and over for each one of these words. Next up is the hidden
layer of this neural network. The size of this hidden neural layer of this neural net is a
hyperparameter. So we use the word hyperparameter when it's kind of like a design choice up to the
designer of the neural net. And this can be as large as you'd like or as small as you'd like.
So for example, the size could be 100. And we are going to go over multiple choices of the size of
this hidden layer. And we're going to evaluate how well they work. So say there were 100 neurons
here. All of them would be fully connected to the 90 words or 90 numbers that make up these three
words. So this is a fully connected layer. Then there's a 10-inch long linearity. And then there's
this output layer. And because there are 17,000 possible words that could come next, this layer
has 17,000 neurons. And all of them are fully connected to all of these neurons.
In the hidden layer. So there's a lot of parameters here because there's a lot of words. So most
computation is here. This is the expensive layer. Now there are 17,000 logits here. So on top of
there, we have the softmax layer, which we've seen in our previous video as well. So every one of
these logits is exponentiated. And then everything is normalized to sum to one. So then we have a
nice probability distribution for the next word in the sequence. Now, of course, during training,
we actually have the label.
We have the identity of the next word in the sequence. That word or its index is used to pluck
out the probability of that word. And then we are maximizing the probability of that word
with respect to the parameters of this neural net. So the parameters are the weights and biases
of this output layer, the weights and biases of the hidden layer, and the embedding lookup table
C. And all of that is optimized using backpropagation.
And these dashed arrows, ignore those. That represents a variation of a neural net that we are
not going to explore in this video. So that's the setup, and now let's implement it. Okay, so I
started a brand new notebook for this lecture. We are importing PyTorch, and we are importing
matplotlib so we can create figures. Then I am reading all the names into a list of words like
I did before, and I'm showing the first eight right here. Keep in mind that we have 32,000 in total.
These are just the first eight.
And then here I'm building out the vocabulary of characters and all the mappings from the characters as strings to integers, and vice versa.
Now the first thing we want to do is we want to compile the dataset for the neural network.
And I had to rewrite this code. I'll show you in a second what it looks like.
So this is the code that I created for the dataset creation. So let me first run it, and then I'll briefly explain how this works.
So first we're going to define something called block size.
This is going to be the context length of how many characters do we take to predict the next one.
So here in this example, we're taking three characters to predict the fourth one.
So we have a block size of three. That's the size of the block that supports the prediction.
Then here I'm building out the x and y. The x are the input to the neural net, and the y are the labels for each example inside the x.
Then I'm erasing over the first five words. I'm doing the first five just for efficiency
while we are developing all the code. But then later we are going to come here and erase this so that we use the entire training set.
So here I'm printing the word Emma. And here I'm basically showing the examples that we can generate,
the five examples that we can generate out of the single sort of word Emma.
So when we are given the context of just dot dot dot, the first character in the sequence is E.
In this context, the label is M.
When the context is this, the label is M, and so forth.
And so the way I build this out is first I start with a padded context of just zero tokens.
Then I iterate over all the characters. I get the character in the sequence.
And I basically build out the array y of this current character and the array x, which stores the current running context.
And then here, see, I print everything. And here I crop the context and enter the new character in the sequence.
So this is kind of like a rolling window.
This is kind of like a rolling window of context.
Now we can change the block size here to, for example, four.
And in that case, we would be predicting the fifth character given the previous four.
Or it can be five. And then it would look like this.
Or it can be, say, ten. And then it would look something like this.
We're taking ten characters to predict the eleventh one.
And we're always padding with dots.
So let me bring this back to three just so that we have what we have here in the paper.
And finally, the data set right now looks as follows.
From these five words, we have created a data set of 32 examples.
And each input to the neural net is three integers.
And we have a label that is also an integer, y.
So x looks like this.
These are the individual examples.
And then y are the labels.
So given this, let's now write a neural network that takes these x's and predicts the y's.
First, let's build the embedding.
Lookup table C.
So we have 27 possible characters.
And we're going to embed them in a lower-dimensional space.
In the paper, they have 17,000 words.
And they embed them in spaces as small-dimensional as 30.
So they cram 17,000 words into 30-dimensional space.
In our case, we have only 27 possible characters.
So let's cram them in something as small as, to start with, for example, a two-dimensional space.
So this lookup table will be random numbers.
And we'll have 27 rows.
And we'll have two columns.
Right?
So each one of 27 characters will have a two-dimensional embedding.
So that's our matrix C of embeddings.
In the beginning, initialized randomly.
Now before we embed all of the integers inside the input x using this lookup table C,
let me actually just try to embed a single individual integer, like, say, 5.
So we get a sense of time.
So we get a sense of how this works.
Now one way this works, of course, is we can just take the C and we can index into row 5.
And that gives us a vector, the fifth row of C.
And this is one way to do it.
The other way that I presented in the previous lecture is actually seemingly different but actually identical.
So in the previous lecture, what we did is we took these integers and we used the one-hot encoding to first encode them.
So we took that one-hot.
We want to encode integer 5.
And we want to tell it that the number of classes is 27.
So that's the 26-dimensional vector of all zeros except the fifth bit is turned on.
Now this actually doesn't work.
The reason is that this input actually must be a Torch.tensor.
And I'm making some of these errors intentionally just so you get to see some errors and how to fix them.
So this must be a tensor, not an int.
Fairly straightforward to fix.
We get a one-hot vector.
The fifth dimension is 1.
And the shape of this is 27.
And now notice that, just as I briefly alluded to in a previous video,
if we take this one-hot vector and we multiply it by C,
then what would you expect?
Well, number one, first you'd expect an error
because expected scalar type long but found float.
So a little bit confusing.
But the problem here is that one-hot, the data type of it, is long.
It's a 64-bit integer.
But this is a float tensor.
And so PyTorch doesn't know how to multiply an int with a float.
And that's why we had to explicitly cast this to a float so that we can multiply.
Now the output actually here is identical.
And it's identical because of the way the matrix multiplication here works.
So we have a one-hot vector multiplying columns of C.
And because of all the zeros, they actually end up masking out everything in C
except for the fifth row, which is plucked out.
And so we actually arrive at the same result.
And that tells you that here we can interpret this first piece here,
this embedding of the integer.
We can either think of it as the integer indexing into a lookup table C,
but equivalently we can also think of this little piece here
as a first layer of this bigger neural net.
This layer here has neurons that have no nonlinearity.
There's no tanh.
They're just linear neurons.
And their weight matrix is C.
And then we are encoding integers into one-hot
and feeding those into a neural net.
And this first layer basically embeds them.
So those are two equivalent ways of doing the same thing.
We're just going to index because it's much, much faster.
And we're going to discard this interpretation of one-hot inputs into neural nets.
And we're just going to index integers
to create and use embedding tables.
Now embedding a single integer like 5 is easy enough.
We can simply ask PyTorch to retrieve the fifth row of C
or the row index 5 of C.
But how do we simultaneously embed all of these 32 by 3 integers
stored in array X?
Luckily, PyTorch indexing is fairly flexible and quite powerful.
So it doesn't just work to ask for a single element 5 like this.
You can actually index using lists.
So for example, we can get the rows 5, 6, and 7.
And this will just work like this.
We can index with a list.
It doesn't just have to be a list.
It can also be actually a tensor of integers.
And we can index with that.
So this is an integer tensor 5, 6, 7.
And this will just work as well.
In fact, we can also, for example, repeat row 7
and retrieve it multiple times.
And that same index will just get embedded multiple times.
So here we are indexing with a one-dimensional tensor of integers.
But it turns out that you can also index with multidimensional
tensors of integers.
Here we have a two-dimensional tensor of integers.
So we can simply just do C at X.
And this just works.
And the shape of this is 32 by 3,
which is the original shape.
And now for every one of those 32 by 3 integers,
we've retrieved the embedding vector
here.
So basically, we have that as an example.
The example index 13,
the second dimension,
is the integer 1 as an example.
And so here, if we do C of X,
which gives us that array,
and then we index into 13 by 2
of that array,
then we get the embedding here.
And you can verify that C at 1
which is the integer at that location,
is indeed equal to this.
You see they're equal.
So basically, long story short,
PyTorch indexing is awesome.
And to embed simultaneously
all of the integers in X,
we can simply do C of X.
And that is our embedding.
And that just works.
Now let's construct this layer here,
the hidden layer.
So we have that W1, as I'll call it,
are these weights.
Which we will initialize randomly.
Now the number of inputs to this layer
is going to be 3 times 2.
Right?
Because we have two-dimensional embeddings
and we have three of them.
So the number of inputs is 6.
And the number of neurons in this layer
is a variable up to us.
Let's use 100 neurons as an example.
And then biases
will be also initialized randomly
as an example.
And we just need 100 of them.
Now the problem with this is,
we can't simply,
normally we would take the input,
in this case that's embedding,
and we'd like to multiply it with these weights.
And then we would like to add the bias.
This is roughly what we want to do.
But the problem here is that
these embeddings are stacked up
in the dimensions of this input tensor.
So this will not work,
this matrix multiplication,
because this is a shape 32x3x2
and I can't multiply that by 6x100.
So somehow we need to concatenate
these inputs here together,
which apparently does not work.
So how do we transform this 32x3x2
into a 32x6
so that we can actually perform
this multiplication over here?
I'd like to show you that there are
usually many ways of
implementing what you'd like to do
in Torch.
And some of them will be faster, better, shorter, etc.
And that's because Torch is
a very large library,
and it's got lots and lots of functions.
So if we just go to the documentation and click on Torch,
you'll see that my slider here
is very tiny.
And that's because there are so many functions
that you can call on these tensors
to transform them, create them,
multiply them, add them,
perform all kinds of different operations on them.
And so this is kind of like
the space of possibility,
if you will.
Now one of the things that you can do
is if we can control F for concatenate.
And we see that there's a function
torch.cat, short for concatenate.
And this concatenate
is a given sequence of tensors
of a given dimension.
And these tensors must have the same shape, etc.
So we can use the concatenate operation
to, in a naive way,
concatenate these three embeddings
for each input.
So in this case, we have
emb of the shape.
And really what we want to do
is we want to retrieve these three parts
and concatenate them.
So we want to grab all the examples.
We want to grab
first the zeroth
and then
index.
And then all of this.
So this plucks out
the 32 by 2
embeddings of just
the first word here.
And so basically
we want this guy,
we want the first dimension,
and we want the second dimension.
And these are the three pieces individually.
And then we want to
treat this as a sequence
and we want to torch.cat
on that sequence.
torch.cat takes a
sequence of tensors
and then we have to tell it along which dimension
to concatenate.
So in this case, all these are 32 by 2
and we want to concatenate not across
dimension 0, but across dimension 1.
So passing in 1
gives us a result
that the shape of this is 32 by 6
exactly as we'd like.
So that basically took 32 and
squashed these by concatenating
them into 32 by 6.
Now this is kind of ugly because
this code would not generalize
if we want to later change the block size.
Right now we have three inputs,
three words, but what if we had
five? Then here we would have to
change the code because I'm indexing directly.
Well, torch comes to rescue again
because there turns out to be
a function called unbind
and it removes a tensor dimension.
So it removes a tensor dimension, returns
a tuple of all slices along a given
dimension without it.
So this is exactly what we need.
And basically when we call
torch.unbind
of m
and passing dimension
index 1, this gives us
a list of
a list of tensors exactly
equivalent to this. So running this
gives us a line
and it's exactly this list.
So we can call torch.cat on it
and
the first dimension.
And this works.
And this shape is the same.
But now this is, it doesn't matter if we
have block size 3 or 5 or 10,
this will just work.
So this is one way to do it. But it turns out that
in this case, there's actually a
significantly better and more efficient way.
And this gives me an opportunity to hint
at some of the internals of torch.tensor.
So let's create
an array here
of elements from
0 to 17. And the shape of
this is just 18.
It's a single vector of 18 numbers.
It turns out that we can
very quickly re-represent this
as different sized n-dimensional
tensors. We do this by
calling a view
and we can say that actually this is not
a single vector of 18.
This is a 2 by 9 tensor.
Or alternatively
this is a 9 by 2 tensor.
Or this is actually
a 3 by 3 by 2 tensor.
As long as the total number of
elements here multiply to be
the same, this will just work.
And in PyTorch,
this operation, calling
.view, is extremely efficient.
And the reason for that is that
in each tensor, there's
something called the underlying storage.
And the storage
is just the numbers always
as a one-dimensional vector. And this is
how this tensor is represented
in the computer memory. It's always a one-dimensional
vector.
But when we call .view,
we are manipulating some of
attributes of that tensor that
dictate how this one-dimensional
sequence is interpreted to be
an n-dimensional tensor.
And so what's happening here is that
no memory is being changed, copied, moved,
or created when we call .view.
The storage is identical.
But when you call .view,
some of the internal
attributes of the view of this tensor
are being manipulated and changed.
In particular, there's something called
storage offset, strides, and
shapes, and those are manipulated
so that this one-dimensional sequence of bytes
is seen as different n-dimensional arrays.
There's a blog post
here from Eric called
PyTorch Internals, where he
goes into some of this with respect to tensor
and how the view of a tensor is
represented. And this is really just like
a logical construct
of representing the physical memory.
And so this is a pretty good
blog post that you can go into.
I might also create an entire video
on the internals of TorchTensor and how this works.
For here,
we just note that this is an extremely efficient operation.
And if I delete
this and come back to our
emb,
we see that the shape of our emb is
32x3x2, but we can simply
ask for PyTorch
to view this instead as a 32x6.
And
the way this gets flattened
into a 32x6 array
just happens that
these two get
stacked up in a single row.
And so that's basically the concatenation operation
that we're after.
And you can verify that this actually gives the exact
same result as what we had before.
So this is an element y equals
and you can see that all the elements of these
two tensors are the same.
And so we get the exact same result.
So long story short,
we can actually just come here
and if we just view this
as a 32x6
instead,
then this multiplication will work
and give us the hidden states that we're
after. So if this is h,
then h-shape
is now the hundred-dimensional
activations for every
one of our 32 examples.
And this gives the desired result.
Let me do two things here.
Number one, let's not use 32.
We can, for example, do something like
emb.shape
at 0
so that we don't hardcode these numbers.
And this would work for any size of this
emb. Or alternatively, we can
also do negative 1. When we do negative 1,
PyTorch will infer
what this should be.
Because the number of elements must be the same,
and we're saying that this is 6, PyTorch will derive
that this must be 32.
Or whatever else it is, if emb is of different size.
The other thing
is here,
one more thing I'd like to point out is
here
when we do the concatenation,
this actually is much less efficient
because this
concatenation would create a whole new tensor
with a whole new storage, so new memory is being
created because there's no way to concatenate
tensors just by manipulating the view
attributes. So this is
inefficient and creates all kinds of new memory.
So let me
delete this now.
We don't need this.
And here to calculate h, we want to
also dot 10h
of this to get our
oops
to get our h.
So these are now numbers between negative 1 and 1
because of the 10h, and we have
that the shape is 32 by 100
and that is basically this
hidden layer of activations here
for every one of our 32
examples. Now there's one more thing I've
lost over that we have to be very careful with
and that's this plus
here. In particular we want to make
sure that the broadcasting will do
what we like. The shape of
this is 32 by 100
and b1's shape is 100.
So we see that the addition
here will broadcast these two
and in particular we have 32 by 100
broadcasting to 100.
So broadcasting
will align on the right
create a fake dimension here
so this will become a 1 by 100 row vector
and then it will copy
vertically for every
one of these rows of 32
and do an element-wise addition.
So in this case the correcting will be happening
because the same bias vector
will be added to all the rows
of this matrix.
So that is correct, that's what we'd like
and it's always good
practice to just make sure so that
you don't shoot yourself in the foot.
And finally let's create the final layer here
so let's create
w2 and b2
the input
now is 100
and the output number of neurons
will be for us 27
because we have 27 possible characters
that come next.
So the biases will be 27 as well.
So therefore the logits
which are the outputs of this neural net
are going to be
h multiplied
by w2 plus b2
logits.shape is 32 by 27
and the logits
look good.
Now exactly as we saw in the previous video
we want to take these logits and we want to
first exponentiate them to get our fake counts
and then we want to normalize them
into a probability.
So prob is counts divide
and now
counts.sum along
the first dimension and keep them
as true, exactly as in the previous video.
And so
prob.shape
now is 32 by 27
and you'll see that every row
of prob
sums to 1, so it's normalized.
So that gives us
the probabilities. Now of course we have
the actual letter that comes next
and that comes from this array y
which we
created during the dataset creation.
So y is this last piece here
which is the identity of the next character
in the sequence that we'd like to now predict.
So what we'd
like to do now is just as in the previous video
we'd like to index into the rows
of prob and in each row
we'd like to pluck out the probability assigned
to the correct character
as given here.
So first we have torch.arrange
which is kind of like
an iterator over
numbers from 0 to 31
and then we can index into prob
in the following way
prob.in
which iterates the rows
and then in each row we'd like to grab
this column
as given by y.
So this gives the current probabilities
as assigned by this neural network
with this setting of its weights
to the correct character in the sequence.
And you can see here that
this looks okay for some of these characters
like this is basically 0.2
but it doesn't look very good at all for many other characters
like this is 0.0701 probability
and so the network thinks that
some of these are extremely unlikely.
Of course we haven't trained the neural network yet
so
this will improve and ideally all of these
numbers here of course are 1
because then we are correctly predicting the next character.
Now just as in the previous video
we want to take these probabilities
we want to look at the log probability
and then we want to look at the average log probability
and the negative of it
to create the negative log likelihood loss.
So the loss here is 17
and this is the loss
that we'd like to minimize to get the network
to predict the correct character
in the sequence.
Okay so I rewrote everything here
and made it a bit more respectable.
So here's our dataset.
Here's all the parameters that we defined.
I'm now using a generator to make it reproducible.
I clustered all the parameters
into a single list of parameters
so that for example it's easy to count them
and see that in total we currently have
about 3400 parameters.
And this is the forward pass as we developed it
and we arrive at a
single number here, the loss, that is currently
expressing how well
this neural network works with the current
setting of parameters.
Now I would like to make it even more respectable.
So in particular see these lines here
where we take the logits and we calculate
the loss.
We're not actually reinventing the wheel here.
This is just
classification and many people
use classification and that's why there is
a functional dot cross entropy function
in PyTorch to calculate this
much more efficiently.
So we could just simply call f dot cross entropy
and we can pass in the logits and we can pass in
the array of targets y
and this calculates the exact
same loss.
So in fact we can
simply put this here
and erase these three lines
and we're going to get the exact same result.
Now there are actually many good reasons
to prefer f dot cross entropy over
rolling your own implementation like this.
I did this for educational reasons
but you'd never use this in practice.
Why is that?
Number one, when you use f dot cross entropy,
PyTorch will not actually create
all these intermediate tensors
because these are all new tensors in memory
and all this is fairly inefficient
to run like this.
Instead PyTorch will cluster up all these operations
and very often
have fused kernels
that very efficiently evaluate these expressions
that are sort of like clustered mathematical operations.
Number two,
the backward pass can be made much more efficient
and not just because it's a fused kernel
but also analytically
and mathematically
because it's often a very much simpler
backward pass to implement.
We actually saw this with micrograd.
You see here when we implemented 10H
the forward pass of this operation
to calculate the 10H
was actually a fairly complicated mathematical expression.
But because it's a clustered
mathematical expression
when we did the backward pass
we didn't individually backward through the
x and the 2 times and the minus 1
and the division, etc.
We just said it's 1 minus t squared
and that's a much simpler mathematical expression.
And we were able to do this
because we're able to reuse calculations
and because we are able to mathematically
and analytically derive the derivative
and often that expression simplifies mathematically
and so there's much less to implement.
So not only
can it be made more efficient
because it runs in a fused kernel
but also because the expressions
can take a much simpler form mathematically.
So that's number one.
Number two,
under the hood,
it's significantly more
numerically well behaved.
Let me show you an example of how this works.
Suppose we have a logits of
negative 2, 3, negative 3, 0 and 5.
And then we are taking the exponent
of it and normalizing it to sum to 1.
So when logits take on
these values, everything is well and good
and we get a nice probability distribution.
Now consider what happens when
some of these logits take on more extreme values.
And that can happen during optimization
of a neural network.
Let's say some of these numbers grow very negative
like say negative 100.
Then actually everything will come out fine.
We still get probabilities that
are well behaved
and they sum to 1 and everything is great.
But because of the way
the X works,
if you have very positive logits
like say positive 100 in here,
you actually start to run into trouble
and we get not a number here.
And the reason for that is that these counts
have an inf here.
So if you pass in
a very negative number to exp,
you just get a very negative,
sorry not negative, but very small number.
Very near 0 and that's fine.
But if you pass in a very positive number,
suddenly we run out of range
in our floating point number
that represents these counts.
So basically we are taking e
and we are raising it to the power of 100
and that gives us inf
because we ran out of dynamic range
on this floating point number that is count.
And so we cannot
pass very large logits through
this expression.
Now let me reset these numbers
to something reasonable.
The way PyTorch solved this
is that, you see how we have a
well-behaved result here?
It turns out that because of the normalization
here, you can actually offset
logits by any arbitrary
constant value that you want.
So if I add 1 here, you actually
get the exact same result.
Or if I add 2, or if I subtract
3.
Any offset will produce the exact same
values.
So because negative numbers are okay,
but positive numbers can actually overflow
this exp, what PyTorch does
is it internally calculates the maximum
value that occurs in the logits
and it subtracts it.
So in this case it would subtract 5.
And so therefore the greatest number in logits
will become 0, and all the other numbers
will become some negative numbers.
And then the result of this is always
well-behaved. So even if we have 100
here previously,
not good, but because PyTorch
subtracted 100, this will work.
And so there's
many good reasons to call cross
entropy. Number one, the forward
pass can be much more efficient, the backward
pass can be much more efficient, and
also things can be much more numerically
well-behaved. Okay, so let's now
set up the training of this neural net.
We have the forward pass.
We don't
need these, because then we have
that loss is equal to the
cross entropy, that's the forward pass.
Then we need the backward pass,
first we want to set the gradients
to be 0. So for p in parameters
we want to make sure that
p.grad is none, which is the same as setting
it to 0 in PyTorch. And then
loss.backward to populate those
gradients. Once we have the gradients
we can do the parameter update.
So for p in parameters we want to take all
the data, and we want to
nudge it learning rate times
p.grad.
And then
we want to repeat this
a few times.
And let's print
the loss here as well.
Now this
won't suffice and it will create an error,
because we also have to go for p in parameters
and we have to make sure that
p.requiresgrad is set
to true in PyTorch.
And this should
just work.
Okay, so we started off with
loss of 17 and we're decreasing it.
Let's run longer.
And you see how the loss
increases a lot here.
So
if we just run for 1000 times
we get a very, very low loss.
And that means that we're making very good predictions.
Now the reason that this is
so straightforward right now
is because we're only
overfitting 32
examples. So we only have
32 examples of the first 5
words, and therefore
it's very easy to make this neural net fit
only these 32 examples.
Because we have 3400 parameters
and only 32
examples. So we're doing what's called
overfitting a single batch of
the data and getting a very low
loss in good predictions.
But that's just because we have so many
parameters for so few examples. So it's easy
to make this be very low.
Now we're not able to achieve
exactly 0. And the reason
for that is, we can for example look at logits
which are being predicted.
And we
can look at the max along
the first dimension.
And in PyTorch
max reports both the actual values
that take on the maximum number
but also the indices of these.
And you'll see that the indices
are very close to the labels.
But in some cases
they differ. For example
in this very first example
the predicted index is 19
but the label is 5.
And we're not able to make loss be 0
and fundamentally that's because here
the very first
or the zeroth index is the example
where dot dot dot is supposed to predict E
but you see how dot dot dot is also supposed
to predict an O
and dot dot dot is also supposed to predict an I
and then S as well.
And so basically E, O, A
or S are all possible
outcomes in a training set for the exact
same input. So we're not able to
completely overfit and
make the loss be exactly 0.
But we're getting very
close in the cases where
there's a unique input for
a unique output. In those cases
we do what's called overfit and
we basically get the exact same
and the exact correct result.
So now all we have to do
is we just need to make sure that we read in the
full dataset and optimize the neural net.
Okay so let's swing back up
where we created the dataset
and we see that here we only use the first 5 words.
So let me now erase this
and let me erase the print statements
otherwise we'd be printing way too much.
And so when we process the
full dataset of all the words
we now have 228,000 examples
instead of just 32.
So let's now scroll back down
the dataset is much larger
reinitialize the weights, the same
number of parameters, they all require gradients
and then let's push
this print.loss.item
to be here and let's just see
how the optimization goes if we run this.
Okay so we started
with a fairly high loss and then as we're optimizing
the loss is coming down.
But you'll notice that it takes
quite a bit of time for every single iteration.
So let's actually address that
because we're doing way too much work
forwarding and backwarding 228,000
examples. In practice
what people usually do is they perform
forward and backward pass and update
on many batches of the data.
So what we will want to do is
we want to randomly select some portion
of the dataset and that's a many batch
and then only forward, backward and update
on that little many batch and then
we iterate on those many batches.
So in pytorch we can for example
use torch.randint
and we can generate numbers between 0
and 5 and make 32 of them.
I believe the size has to
be a tuple
in pytorch.
So we can have a tuple
32 of numbers between 0 and 5
but actually we want x.shape
of 0 here
and so this creates integers
that index into our dataset
and there's 32 of them.
So if our many batch size is 32
then we can come here and we can first do
a many batch
construct.
So integers
that we want to optimize in this
single iteration
are in the ix
and then we want to index into
x with
ix to only grab those
rows. So we're only getting 32
rows of x and therefore
embeddings will again be 32 by 3
by 2, not 200,000
by 3 by 2.
And then this ix has to be used not just
to index into x but also
to index into y.
And now this
should be many batches and this should be
much much faster.
So it's instant almost.
So this way we can run
many many examples
nearly instantly and decrease
the loss much much faster.
Now because we're only dealing with many batches
the quality of our gradient
is lower. So the direction is not
as reliable. It's not the actual gradient
direction. But
the gradient direction is good enough even
when it's estimating on only 32
examples that it is useful.
And so it's much better
to have an approximate gradient and
just make more steps than it is to
evaluate the exact gradient and take
fewer steps. So that's why
in practice this works
quite well. So let's now continue
the optimization.
Let me take out
this loss.item from here.
And place it
over here at the end.
Okay so we're hovering around 2.5
or so.
However this is only the loss
for that many batch. So let's actually evaluate
the loss here
for all of x
and for all of y.
Just so we have a full
sense of exactly how well the model is
doing right now.
So right now we're at about 2.7 on the
entire training set.
So let's run the optimization for a while.
Okay we're at
2.6
2.57
2.53
Okay.
So one issue of course is
we don't know if we're stepping too slow
or too fast.
So at this point one I just guessed it.
So one question is
how do you determine this learning rate?
And how do we gain confidence
that we're stepping in the right
sort of speed?
So let's try to determine a reasonable learning rate.
It works as follows.
Let's reset our parameters
to the initial
settings.
And now let's print
in every step.
But let's only do 10 steps or so.
Or maybe
100 steps.
We want to find a very reasonable
search range if you will.
So for example if this is very low
then
we see that the loss is barely
decreasing. So that's not
that's like too low basically.
So let's try this one.
Okay so we're
decreasing the loss but like not very quickly.
So that's a pretty good low range.
Now let's reset it again.
And now let's try to find the place
at which the loss kind of explodes.
So maybe at negative one.
Okay we see that we're minimizing the loss
but you see how it's kind of unstable.
It goes up and down quite a bit.
So negative one is probably like a
fast learning rate.
Let's try negative ten.
Okay so this isn't
optimizing. This is not working very well.
So negative ten is way too big.
Negative one was already kind of big.
So
therefore negative one was like
somewhat reasonable if I reset.
So I'm thinking that the right
learning rate is somewhere between
negative 0.001
and negative one.
So the way we can do this
here is we can use Torch.lin
space.
And we want to basically do something like this.
Between zero and one.
Oh number of steps is one more parameter
that's required. Let's do a thousand steps.
This creates one thousand
numbers between
0.001 and one.
But it doesn't really make sense to
step between these linearly.
So instead let me create learning rate
exponent. And instead of
0.001 this will be
a negative three and this will be a zero.
And then the actual LRs
that we want to search over are going to be
ten to the power of LRE.
So now what we're doing is
we're stepping linearly between the exponents
of these learning rates. This is 0.001
and this is one.
Because ten to the power of zero
is one. And therefore
we are spaced exponentially in this interval.
So these are the candidate
learning rates that we want
to sort of like search over roughly.
So now what we're going to do is
here
we are going to run the optimization for
one thousand steps. And instead of using
a fixed number we are going to
use learning rate
indexing into here LRs
of i and make this
i.
So basically let me reset this
to be again starting
from random. Creating these learning
rates between negative
between 0.001 and
one
but exponentially stepped.
And here what we're doing is
we're iterating a thousand times
we're going to use the learning rate
that's in the beginning
very very low. In the beginning it's going to be
0.001 but by the end it's
going to be one.
And then we're going to step with that
learning rate.
And now what we want to do is we want to keep track
of the
learning rates that we used.
And we want to look at the losses
that resulted.
And so here let me
track stats.
So LRI dot append
LR and
loss side dot append
loss dot item.
Okay.
So again reset everything
and then
run.
And so basically we started
with a very low learning rate and we went all the way up
to learning rate of negative one.
And now what we can do is we can
plt dot plot and
we can plot the two. So we can plot
the learning rates on the x-axis
and the losses we saw on the y-axis.
And often you're going to find
that your plot looks something like this.
Where in the beginning
you had very low learning rates
basically anything
barely anything happened.
Then we got to like a nice spot
here and then as we increased
the learning rate enough
we basically started to be kind of unstable here.
So a good learning rate turns out
to be somewhere around here.
And because
we have LRI here
we actually
may want to
do not LR
not the learning rate but the exponent.
So that would be the LRE at i
is maybe what we want to log.
So let me reset this and redo that
calculation. But now on the x-axis
we have the
exponent of the learning rate.
And so we can see that the exponent
of the learning rate that is good to use
would be sort of like roughly in the value here
because here the learning rates are just way too low
and then here we expect
relatively good learning rates somewhere here
and then here things are starting to explode.
So somewhere around negative 1
as the exponent of the learning rate is a pretty good setting.
And 10 to the
negative 1 is 0.1
So 0.1 was actually
a fairly good learning rate around here.
And that's what we had
in the initial setting
but that's roughly how you would determine it.
And so here now we can
take out the tracking of these
and we can
just simply set LRE to be
10 to the negative 1
or basically otherwise 0.1
as it was before.
And now we have some confidence that this is actually a fairly good
learning rate. And so now what we can do
is we can crank up the iterations
we can reset our optimization
and
we can run for
a pretty long time using this learning rate
oops
and we don't want to print, it's way too much printing
so let me again reset
and run 10,000 steps.
Okay so we're at
2.48 roughly.
Let's run another 10,000 steps.
2.46
And now let's do
one learning rate decay. What this means is
we're going to take our learning rate and we're going to
10x lower it. And so
we're at the late stages of training potentially
and we may want to go
a little bit slower. Let's do one more actually
at 0.1 just to see if
we're making a dent here.
Okay we're still making a dent. And by the way the
bigram loss that we
achieved last video was 2.45
so we've already surpassed
the bigram model.
And once I get a sense that this is actually kind of starting
to plateau off, people like to do
as I mentioned this learning rate decay.
So let's try to decay the loss
the learning rate I mean.
And we achieve
it about 2.3 now.
Obviously this is janky
and not exactly how you would train it in
production but this is roughly what you're going
through. You first find a decent learning
rate using the approach that I showed you.
Then you start with that learning rate
and you train for a while. And then at
the end people like to do a learning rate decay
where you decay the learning rate by say a factor
of 10 and you do a few more steps
and then you get a trained network
roughly speaking. So we've achieved
2.3 and dramatically
improved on the bigram language model
using this simple neural net
as described here.
Using these 3400 parameters.
Now there's something we have to be careful with.
I said that we have
a better model because we are achieving
a lower loss. 2.3
much lower than 2.45 with the bigram
model previously. Now that's not
exactly true. And the reason that's not
true is that
this is actually a fairly small model
but these models can get larger and larger
if you keep adding neurons and parameters.
So you can imagine that we don't
potentially have a thousand parameters. We could have
10,000 or 100,000 or millions of parameters.
And as the capacity of the neural
network grows, it
becomes more and more capable of
overfitting your training set.
What that means is that the loss on the
training set, on the data that you're training
on, will become very very low.
As low as zero.
But all that the model is doing is memorizing
your training set verbatim.
So if you take that model and it looks like it's working
well, but you try to sample from it,
you will basically only get examples
exactly as they are in the training set.
You won't get any new data.
In addition to that, if you try to evaluate the
loss on some withheld names
or other words, you will
actually see that the loss on those
can be very high. And so basically
it's not a good model.
So the standard in the field is to split up
your data set into three splits,
as we call them. We have the training split,
the def split, or the validation
split, and the test split.
So,
training split,
test or, sorry,
def or validation split,
and test split.
And typically, this would be
say 80% of your data set, this could be
10%, and this 10% roughly.
So you have these three splits
of the data.
Now, these 80% of your training
of the data set, the training set,
is used to optimize the parameters of the model.
Just like we're doing here, using Gradient Descent.
These 10%
of the examples,
the def or validation split, they're used
for development over all the hyper
parameters of your model. So
hyper parameters are, for example, the size
of this hidden layer, the size of
the embedding. So this is a 100 or
a 2 for us, but we could try different things.
The strength of the regularization,
which we aren't using yet so far.
So there's lots of different hyper
parameters and settings that go into defining
a neural net. And you can try many different
variations of them and see whichever
one works best on your
validation split.
So this is used to train the parameters.
This is used to train the
hyper parameters. And test
split is used to evaluate
basically the performance of the model at the end.
So we're only evaluating
the loss on the test split very, very sparingly
and very few times. Because
every single time you evaluate your test
loss and you learn something from it,
you are basically starting to
also train on the test split.
So you are only allowed
to test the loss on the test
set very, very
few times. Otherwise you risk
overfitting to it as well
as you experiment on your model.
So let's also split up our training
data into train, dev,
and test. And then we are going to
train on train and only evaluate
on test very, very sparingly.
Okay, so here we go.
Here is where we took all the words
and put them into x and y tensors.
So instead, let me create
a new cell here and let me just copy paste
some code here. Because I don't
think it's that complex.
But
we're going to try to save a little bit of time.
I'm converting this to be a function now.
And this function takes some list
of words and builds the arrays
x and y for those words only.
And then here
I am shuffling up all the
words. So these are the input words
that we get. We are randomly shuffling
them all up. And then
we're going to
set n1 to be
the number of examples. There's
80% of the words and n2 to be
90% of the weight of
the words. So basically if length
of words is 32,000
n1 is
oh sorry, I should probably run this.
25,000 and n2 is 28,000.
And so here we see that
I'm calling build data set
to build the training set x and y
by indexing into
up to n1. So we're going to have
only 25,000 training words.
And then we're going to have
roughly
n2 minus n1
3,000 validation
examples or dev
examples and we're going to have
length of words basically
minus n2
or 3,204
examples here
for the test set.
So now we have
x's and y's for
all those three splits.
Oh yeah
I'm printing their size here inside the function as well.
But here we don't have words but these are already
the individual examples made from those words.
So let's now scroll down here
and the data set now for training
is
more like this.
And then when we reset the network
when we're training
we're only going to be training using
x train
and y train.
So that's the only thing we're
training on.
Let's see where we are
on the single batch.
Let's now train maybe
a few more steps.
Training of neural networks can take a while.
Usually you don't do it inline.
You launch a bunch of jobs
and you wait for them to finish.
It can take multiple days and so on.
Luckily this is a very small network.
Okay so the loss is pretty good.
Oh we accidentally used
a learning rate that is way too low.
So let me actually come back.
We used the decay learning rate
of 0.01.
So this will train much faster.
And then here when we evaluate
let's use the depth set here.
x dev
and y dev
to evaluate the loss.
And let's not decay the learning rate
and only do say 10,000 examples.
And let's evaluate the dev loss
once here.
Okay so we're getting about 2.3 on dev.
And so the neural network when it was training
did not see these dev examples.
It hasn't optimized on them.
And yet when we evaluate the loss
on these dev we actually get a pretty decent loss.
And so
we can also look at what the
loss is on all of training set.
Oops.
And so we see that the training and the dev loss
are about equal.
So we're not overfitting.
This model is not powerful enough
to just be purely memorizing the data.
And so far we are what's called underfitting.
Because the training loss
and the dev or test losses
are roughly equal.
So what we can do is
is that our network is very tiny.
Very small.
And we expect to make performance improvements
by scaling up the size of this neural net.
So let's do that now.
So let's come over here
and let's increase the size of the neural net.
The easiest way to do this
is we can come here to the hidden layer
which currently has 100 neurons.
And let's just bump this up.
So let's do 300 neurons.
And then this is also 300 biases.
And here we have 300 inputs
that initialize our neural net.
We now have 10,000 parameters
instead of 3,000 parameters.
And then we're not using this.
And then here what I'd like to do
is I'd like to actually
keep track of
Okay, let's just do this.
Let's keep stats again.
And here when we're keeping track of the
loss
let's just also keep track of
the steps.
I have an eye here.
And let's train on 30,000
or rather say
Okay, let's try 30,000.
And we are at 0.1
And we should
be able to run this
and optimize the neural net.
And then here basically
I want to plt.plot
the steps against
the loss.
So these are the x's and the y's.
And this is
the loss function
and how it's being optimized.
Now you see that there's quite a bit of
thickness to this.
And that's because we are optimizing over these mini-batches.
And the mini-batches create a little bit of noise
in this.
Where are we in the def set?
We are at 2.5.
So we still haven't optimized this neural net very well.
And that's probably because we made it bigger.
It might take longer for this neural net to converge.
And so let's continue training.
Yeah, let's just
continue training.
One possibility
is that the batch size is so low
that we just have way too much
noise in the training.
And we may want to increase the batch size so that we have a bit more
correct gradient.
And we are not thrashing too much.
And we can actually optimize more properly.
This will now become
meaningless because we've
re-initialized these.
This looks not
pleasing right now.
But there probably is a tiny improvement
but it's so hard to tell.
Let's go again.
2.52
Let's try to decrease the learning rate
by a factor of 2.
Okay, we're at 2.32.
Let's continue training.
We basically expect to see a lower
loss than what we had before.
Because now we have a much much bigger model
and we were underfitting.
So we'd expect that increasing the size of the model should help the neural net.
2.32
Okay, so that's not happening too well.
Now one other concern is that
even though we've made the 10H layer here
or the hidden layer much much bigger
it could be that the bottleneck of the network
right now are these embeddings
that are two-dimensional.
It can be that we're just cramming way too many characters
into just two dimensions
and the neural net is not able to really use that space effectively.
And that is sort of like
the bottleneck to our network's performance.
Okay, 2.23
So just by decreasing the learning rate
I was able to make quite a bit of progress.
Let's run this one more time.
And then evaluate the training
and the dev loss.
Now one more thing
after training that I'd like to do
is I'd like to visualize
the embedding vectors
for these
characters before we scale up
the embedding size from 2.
Because we'd like to make
this bottleneck potentially go away.
But once I make this greater than 2
we won't be able to visualize them.
So here, okay we're at 2.23
and 2.24
so we're not improving
much more and maybe the bottleneck now
is the character embedding size which is 2.
So here I have a bunch
of code that will create a figure
and then we're going to visualize
the embeddings that were trained
by the neural net on these characters.
Because right now the embedding size is just 2
so we can visualize all the characters
with the x and the y coordinates
as the two embedding locations
for each of these characters.
And so here are the
x coordinates and the y coordinates
which are the columns of C
and then for each one I also include
the text of the little character.
So here what we see
is actually kind of interesting.
The network has
basically learned to separate out
the characters and cluster them a little bit
so for example you see how the vowels
a, e, i, o, u
are clustered up here
so what that's telling us is that the neural net
treats these as very similar
because when they feed into the neural net
the embedding for all these characters
is very similar and so the neural net
thinks that they're very similar
and kind of like interchangeable
if that makes sense.
Then the points that are like
really far away are for example Q
Q is kind of treated as an exception
and Q has a very special embedding vector
so to speak.
Similarly dot, which is a special character
is all the way out here
and a lot of the other letters are sort of like
clustered up here.
And so it's kind of interesting that there's
a little bit of structure here
after the training and it's not
definitely not random and these embeddings
make sense.
So we're now going to scale up the embedding size
and won't be able to visualize it directly
but we expect that because we're underfitting
and we made this layer
much bigger and did not sufficiently
improve the loss, we're thinking that the
constraint
to better performance right now
could be these embedding vectors.
So let's make them bigger.
So let's scroll up here and now we don't have
two dimensional embeddings, we are going to have
say 10 dimensional embeddings
for each word.
Then this layer will receive
3 times 10
so 30 inputs
will go into
the hidden layer.
Let's also make the hidden layer a bit smaller
so instead of 300 let's just do 200
neurons in that hidden layer.
So now the total number of elements
will be slightly bigger at
11,000.
And then here we have to be a bit careful because
the learning rate
we set to 0.1
here we are hardcoding 6
and obviously if you're working in production
you don't want to be hardcoding magic numbers
but instead of 6 this should now be 30.
And let's run for
50,000 iterations and let me
split out the initialization here
outside so that
when we run this multiple times it's not going
to wipe out our loss.
In addition to that
here let's instead
of logging loss.item let's actually
log the
let's do log10
I believe
that's a function of the loss
and I'll show you
why in a second. Let's optimize this.
This
basically I'd like to plot the log loss
instead of the loss because when you plot
the loss many times it can have this hockey stick
appearance and log
squashes it in.
So it just kind of like looks nicer.
So the x-axis is step i
and the y-axis will be the loss
i.
And then here this is 30.
Ideally we wouldn't be hardcoding these
because let's look
at the loss.
It's again very thick because
the mini-batch size is very small
but the total loss over the training set
is 2.3 and the test
or the def set is 2.38 as well.
So far so good.
Let's try to now decrease the learning rate
by a factor of 10
and train for another 50,000 iterations.
We'd hope that we would be able to beat
2.32.
But again we're just kind of like doing this very
haphazardly so I don't actually have
confidence that our learning rate is set
very well, that our learning rate decay
which we just do at random
is set very well.
And so the optimization here
is kind of suspect to be honest and this is
not how you would do it typically in production.
In production you would create parameters
or hyperparameters out of all these settings
and then you would run lots of experiments
and see whichever ones are working well for you.
Okay.
So we have 2.17 now
and 2.2.
So you see how the training and the validation
performance are starting to
slightly slowly depart.
So maybe we're getting the sense that the neural net
is getting good enough
or that number of parameters
is large enough
that we are slowly starting to overfit.
Let's maybe run
one more iteration of this
and see where we get.
But yeah, basically you would be running
lots of experiments and then you are slowly
scrutinizing whichever ones give you the best
depth performance. And then once you find
all the hyperparameters that make
your depth performance good
you take that model and you evaluate the test set
performance a single time.
And that's the number that you report in your paper
or wherever else you want to talk about
and brag about your model.
So let's then rerun the plot
and rerun the train and dev.
And because we're getting lower loss now
it is the case that the embedding size
of these was holding us back very likely.
Okay, so 2.16, 2.19
is what we're roughly getting.
So there's many ways
to go from here.
We can continue tuning the optimization.
We can continue
for example playing with the size of the neural net.
Or we can increase the number of
words or characters
in our case that we are taking as an input.
So instead of just three characters we could be taking
more characters as an input.
And that could further improve
the loss. Okay, so I changed
the code slightly so we have here
200,000 steps of the optimization
and in the first 100,000 we're using
a learning rate of 0.1 and then in the next
100,000 we're using a learning rate of 0.01.
This is the loss
that I achieve and these are the
performance on the training and validation loss.
And in particular the best
validation loss I've been able to obtain in the last
30 minutes or so is 2.17.
So now I invite
you to beat this number. And you have
quite a few knobs available to you to I think
surpass this number.
So number one, you can of course change the number of
neurons in the hidden layer of this model.
You can change the dimensionality of the
embedding lookup table.
You can change the number of characters that are feeding
in as an input
as the context into this model.
And then of course you can
change the details of the optimization.
How long are we running? Where is the learning rate?
How does it change over time?
How does it decay?
You can change the batch size and you may be able to
actually achieve a much better convergence
speed in terms of
how many seconds or minutes it takes to train
the model and get
your result in terms of really good
loss.
And then of course I actually invite you to
read this paper. It is 19 pages
but at this point you should actually be able to
read a good chunk of this paper and understand
a pretty good
chunks of it.
And this paper also has quite a few ideas for
improvements that you can play with.
So all of those are knobs available to you
and you should be able to beat this number.
I'm leaving that as an exercise to the reader
and that's it for now and I'll see you
next time.
Before we wrap up I also
wanted to show how you would sample from the model.
So we're going to
generate 20 samples.
At first we begin with all dots
so that's the context.
And then until we generate
the 0th character again
we're going to embed
the current context
using the embedding table C.
Now usually
here the first dimension was the size
of the training set. But here we're only working
with a single example that we're generating
so this is just dimension 1
just for simplicity.
And so this
embedding then gets projected into
the state. You get the logits.
Now we calculate the probabilities.
For that you can use f.softmax
of logits
and that just basically
exponentiates the logits and makes them sum to 1.
And similar to cross entropy
it is careful that there's no overflows.
Once we have the probabilities
we sample from them using
torsh.multinomial to get our next index
and then we shift the context window
to append index and record it.
And then we can just
decode all the integers to strings
and print them out.
And so these are some example samples.
And you can see that the model now
works much better.
So the words here are much more word-like
or name-like. So we have things like
ham,
joes,
lila.
It's starting to sound a little bit more name-like.
So we're definitely making progress
but we can still improve on this model quite a lot.
Okay sorry, there's some bonus content.
I wanted to mention that
I want to make these notebooks more accessible.
And so I don't want you to have to
install Jupyter notebooks and torsh and everything else
so I will be sharing a link
to a Google Colab
and the Google Colab will look like a notebook
in your browser.
And you can just go to the URL
and you'll be able to execute all of the code that you saw
in the Google Colab.
And so this is me executing the code
in this lecture and I shortened it a little bit.
But basically you're able to train
the exact same network and then
plot and sample from the model
and everything is ready for you to tinker with the numbers
right there in your browser
no installation necessary.
So I just wanted to point that out
and the link to this will be in the video description.